<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fyve homiles of late, made by a ryght good and vertuous clerke, called master Leonarde Pollarde, prebendary of the Cathedrall Churche of Woster, directed and dedicated to the ryght reuerende Father in God Rychard by the permissyon of God bysshoppe of Woster his specyall good Lorde. Vewed, examined, and alowed by the right reuerende Father in God Edmonde byshop of London, within whose diocese they are imprinted. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum</title>
            <author>Pollard, Leonard, d. 1556.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 169 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105125</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840855</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840855</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5395</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09827)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5395)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 933:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fyve homiles of late, made by a ryght good and vertuous clerke, called master Leonarde Pollarde, prebendary of the Cathedrall Churche of Woster, directed and dedicated to the ryght reuerende Father in God Rychard by the permissyon of God bysshoppe of Woster his specyall good Lorde. Vewed, examined, and alowed by the right reuerende Father in God Edmonde byshop of London, within whose diocese they are imprinted. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum</title>
                  <author>Pollard, Leonard, d. 1556.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[94] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Ftetestrete [sic] at the signe of the Faucon ageynst saynt Dunstones Church by VVyllyam Gryffyth, and are to be solde at his shop a lyttle aboue the Condyte at the signe of the Gryffin],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.LVI. [1556]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Contains same initials as STC 3375 and may have been printed by William Powell--STC.</note>
                  <note>Leaf C2 cancelled by 10 leaves in gatherings of 4, 4, and 2; the first leaves of each gathering are signed C2, C3 and C4 respectively--NUC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴ C⁴(-C2, +C2⁴, C3⁴, and C4² ) D-K⁴ (K4 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>FYVE</hi> Homiles of late, made by a ryght good and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous clerke, called maſter Leonarde Pollarde, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendary of the Cathedrall Churche of Woſter, directed and dedicated to the ryght reuerende Father in God Rychard by the permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of God byſhoppe of Woſter his ſpecyall good Lorde.</p>
            <p>Vewed, examined, and alowed by the right reuerende Father in God Edmonde byſhop of London, within whoſe dioceſe they are imprinted.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum, Anno. M.D.LVI,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:2"/>
            <head>¶ TO THE RIGHT REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RENDE FATHER IN GOD AND his eſpeciall good Lorde, Rycharde by the grace of God byſhop of VVorcetter, his humble oratour and dayely bedeman, Leonarde Pollarde vvyſſheth perpetual health both of ſoule and body.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſyderynge with my ſelfe (moſt reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rende father) the bountifull goodnes of Almyghtly God, who dyd ſo thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receaue the myte offered by the poore wyddowe, as he did the precious giftes offered to him by the ryche and welthy perſons, I haue byn there by encoraged to offer towardes the buylding ageyne of his bleſſed Temple (the Church I meane) de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faced and almoſt deſtroyde by heretickes, theſe ſimple and rude ſermons, not bicauſe that I thynke them to be of ſuche force or learnynge that they can helpe muche thereunto, or that the greate and precious treaſures of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fryd by other myght not ſuffyce, but rather (as I ſayd) to declare the promptnes and redyneſſe of my mynde, which ought to be in me and all men to do ſeruyce vnto his maieſtie accordynge to our habilitie. It is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to your Lordeſhyp the number of bookes and ſermons that were made to deface the churche, and the number and the diligentnes of them that wold haue de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtroyed the churche, the which diligence of them or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther continuall ragynge yf it ſhulde not be matched or with like diligence of our parte ouercome and outmat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,
<pb facs="tcp:5395:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>it ſhulde be much to the reproche of vs all. For yf we ſe (as we can not but ſe) them to haue taken ſuche peynes to ſuppreſſe and ouerthrowe the truth (yf it lay in them ſo to do) howe iuſtely ſhall our conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne vs beinge negligent or retchleſſe by Gods helpe to defende the ſame. Let vs not thynke but God (who hath alredy plaged the churche of this realme for the rechleſſenes of our fathers wyl) much more greuouſly punyſhe vs beinge nothinge amended but rather worſe after this his chaſtiſement and correction. For this is the tyme to take hede and to be diligent and as it were the tyme to harueſt and of labour and not of reapynge and reſt. If we repe before our tyme our corne wyll be greene. If we reſt eare our buſynes be done, we ſhalbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to worke when we ſhulde reſt, &amp; yet it ſhal not auayle vs. We muſt therfore (as the prouerbe is) take the tyme whyle tyme is, for tyme wyl away. Thus my moſt reuerend Father &amp; honorable Lord I being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued partly as I haue ſayde with the bountifull magny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycence of Almyghty God, who dyd ſo louingly accept the offryng of the poore wyddowe, and partly with the conſideration of my duety after this miſerable tyme of ſiſme and hereſy, haue wrytten certeyne ſermons or Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miles the whiche I thought to offer to your reuerende Fatherhod and honorable Lordeſhyp, as the gyftes of a chylde to his father bothe for the fatherly loue that I do knowe you to beare towardes vs your dioceſſans and chyldren, and for your great affection and feruent zeale in the defence and meintenaunce of Gods Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke fayth and true religion, the which your father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:5395:3"/>loue and byſhoplyke zeale beinge well knowen to all men, ſhall cauſe theſe my ſermons to be I truſte the better accepted, both with God and man. Wherefore I ſhall moſte hartely deſyre your honour to accepte this my ſmall oblation or offerynge, and with your wyſedome and diſcretion to vſe the ſame accordyngely, as thereby the Catholyke fayth may be mein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned, and almyghty god beſt honored.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>who haue your good Lordeſhyp in his bleſſed kepynge nowe and euer Amen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>OF THE SACRAMENT OF THE AVLTER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Yke as the trade of marchaundies is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytable, and geyneth much, and the fleſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man is muche delyghted with ſweete meates, and greatly deſyreth them, and yet is there both in marchaundies danger of loſſe, and in delicate fare oftentimes griefes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes are to be feared, ſo is it lykewyſe with thynges that apperteyneth vnto our ſowles (moſte Chryſtyan hearers) thoſe thynges that be moſte holſome for oure ſowles, chaunceth ſometymes vnto the great damage and hurte thereof, as it is to be ſeene amongſt all other thynges, in the moſte bleſſed ſacramente, wherein we eate the fleſhe of our ſauyoure Chryſte, and drynke his blood,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohan.</hi> 6.</note> the profyte wherof, is to make Chryſte abyde in vs, and vs to abyde in Chryſte, the which howe profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table it is, all trewe Chryſtian men do wel knowe, and yet faynt Paule ſayth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> that he which eateth vnworthely this heauenly breade, whiche is Chryſtes fleſhe, and drynketh vnworthely of the cuppe, wherein his moſte bleſſed blood is conteyned, eatethe and drynketh his owne damnacion, bycauſe he pondereth not with hym ſelfe, that it is our Lordes body, whiche he doth there receaue. Wherefore good Chryſtyan people, lyke as the marchaunt wolde gyue good eare to him that ſhuld tell hym howe he might ſayle vpon the ſea without dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and the fleſhely man wolde heare gladly, the phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition tellynge hym howe he myght preſerue his body frome deſeaſes and ſyckeneſſe: So ſhulde we that be Chryſten men, moſte deſyre that knowledge in theſe
<pb facs="tcp:5395:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>bleſſed myſteries,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lu</hi> 12. <hi>Math.</hi> 6.</note> whereby our ſowles maye be kepte ſafe, from the daunger that ſaynt Paule ſayth al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be in that receaueth vnworthyly. For is not your ſoule better, then eyther your goodes, or your bodyes? And ſhall ye not then be as deſirous to kepe your ſoule ſafe, as eyther your bodyes or your goodes? To you than that haue a ſpecial regard vnto your ſoules, I (to whom the cure of your ſoules is committed) muſt ſay, that two thynges are to be marked and conſydered, yf ye wyll a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde daunger in this matter being of ſo great weight. The redreſſe of the one apperteineth to you, and that is that ye come deuoutly and well prepared, for as it was not inough,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 22</note> for hym that came to the maryage without a conuenient and a comely garment, to ſytte with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to eate of the ſame that other dyd eate who were at the feaſte, ſo it is no ſmall daunger to you, to come to this feaſte without your weddynge garmente, but what weddynge garmente trowe you that I do meane? the ſame verely that god gaue vnto you at your baptiſme, and was repreſented or ſygnyfyed by your Cryſome. And yf ye wyll knowe what that is, it was verely innocency, and purenes, for what other thynge doth your depynge or waſhynge in the water ſygnyfye, but that God doth then preſently purge and clenſe you from your ſinnes. Therefore ſeinge that in celebracion of theſe myſteries, ye muſt appeare in our maſters pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and ſyght, ye muſte be ſure that ye do come thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his lyuerye: And thus to prepare you is your duety. The other thynge that is neceſſary vnto the holſome receauynge of theſe myſteries, is a true fayth,<note place="margin">Hebre, <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5395:5"/>without the which no man can pleaſe god, and ye know what daunger it is, for one with whom god is offended or angry, to apeere before hym, but to teache this faith vnto you, that belongeth vnto my charge. For vnto me it is ſayd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>Paſce oues meas,</hi> feede my ſhepe, the which thynge that I may the better do, three thynges are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaryly to be conſydred both of you &amp; me, that is, firſt that ye wyll call vnto your remembraunce what maner of people you to whome I ſhall ſpeake, ought to be, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condely, what the thinges be that we muſt intreate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, thyrdely, from whence, and from whom we muſt come by the knowledge of them. As concernynge the fyrſt, it is not vnknowen vnto you, that Chryſten men are called and named to be faythful, which is as much as to ſaye, people that do beleue, in ſo muche that ſaynt Paule commaundynge Timothe to gyue good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of lyfe vnto all Chryſten men,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.</note> ſayth, <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſto forma fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delium.</hi> That is, be an example to the faythfull, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we be monyſhed, that the chiefeſt thynge in a Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man<note place="margin">Que vide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cia ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t que non vide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> whiche maketh hym to dyffer from all other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is his fayth, but who is he amongſt you, that know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth not that fayth is onely concernynge thoſe thynges that are not to be ſene, and which we knowe only by the report of other? In ſo much that ſaynt Gregory ſayth, that <hi>fides non habet meritum, vbi humana ratio pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet experimentum,</hi> that is to ſay, fayth hath no merite, where mans reaſon giueth thexperie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. And who know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth not that Abraham was commended of god, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge ſo much as he was for his fayth.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 14. <hi>Roma.</hi> 4. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.</note> Doth not the ſcrypture ſay, <hi>Credidit Abraham deo, et imputatum eſt
<pb facs="tcp:5395:5"/>ei ad iuſtitiam,</hi> that is, he beleued Godde, and it was counted to him for rightuouſnes, but howe beleued he. Verely ſaynt Paule ſayth, he dyd not conſider his owne body, which was nowe more fytter for death, then to be get chyldren, he being an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dreth yeres of age, nor yet he dyd conſyder the barren wombe of Sarai his wyfe, who was then foure ſcore and ten yeres of age, he dyd not reaſon with God, howe he and his wyfe beynge in theyr youth, not able to beget chyldren, ſhulde nowe in theyr age, when naturall hope of chyldren was paſte, haue chyldren, he dyd not (I ſay) reaſon with God of theſe matters, as our newe brethrene do, in the greate myſteries of our fayth. He harde God ſpeke, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued, but theſe muſt haue hym ſay ſenſybly, to theyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, this is a fygure of my body, or els they can not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande hym for theyr iuſtyfyinge fayth, or rather as it is to be called, damnable infidelitie, can not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande that god is able to make his body to be really pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent in heauen, and heare to, bothe at one tyme. But vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you good Chryſten people, that be the chyldren of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham, and do beleue. I truſt that there is nothynge, wherein ye can ſo pleaſe god, as in beleuynge his omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency and truth. To you I ſaye that the chiefe cauſe whiche moued our ſauioure to prayſe the Centurion ſo muche as he dyd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 8.</note> was the Centurions faythe, for the Centurion thought that it was as poſſible for Chryſte to heale his ſeruaunt, though he were abſent, as it was for hym ſelfe in his abſence, by commaundement of his ſeruauntes to haue thynges done as he wolde? for the ſame cauſe dyd our ſauioure prayſe alſo the woman of
<pb facs="tcp:5395:6"/>Cananye, ſayinge, woman thy fayth is great. Suche then be you and ſo do beleue,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 15.</note> vnto whom nowe at this tyme I purpoſe by gods grace, to ſpeke of a ſacrament, otherwyſe called in Greeke a myſtery, and in Englyſhe it may be named ſecrete or hydde priuitie of our faythe and religion. In the conſideracion and vnderſtanding of the whiche myſteryes, your mynde and knowledge muſt be remoued, and drawen away from the pryeſtes that miniſtreth (for they be but as inſtrumentes, as for example, the axe is to the wryght, the pen is to the wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the knyfe is to hym that cutteth) and they moſt be bent and ſtayed of Chriſt, who dyd fyrſt ordeyne them, and that doth now vſe the tounge, and other members of the prieſtes, to accomplyſhe and worke the ſame. In ſo muche, that ſaynte Iohn ſpeakynge of the true bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 3.</note> that it is Chryſt that baptyſeth, and Chryſt ſayth hymſelfe, that it is not the miniſter that ſpeaketh, but the ſpryte of the Father,<note place="margin">Sed ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus patris qui loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Luke. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> that ſpeaketh in hym. Alſo Chryſoſtome, and E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſſen ſayth, that it is not the vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible prieſte that worketh the conſecration of the bleſſed Sacrament, but the inuiſible prieſte, whiche is our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour Chryſt. But who ſeeth not then (yf this be true, as it is moſte true) that not fayth, but infidelitie hathe cauſed our late preachers to haue aſked the queſtion, howe can the prieſte make Chryſtes body? As though there were nothynge done in the adminiſtracion of the ſacrament, but what that the prieſte dothe. Doth not this queſtion preſuppoſe the prieſte onely, to be not the inſtrument, but the workeman? Doth not this queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on take that, that is gods worke from God, and gyue
<pb facs="tcp:5395:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnto man? But ye ſhall vnderſtande good people, that theſe be therfore called myſteries, bycauſe that in them one thynge doth outwardely appere to our ſenſes, and an other is certeynely knowen to our beliefe and vnder ſtandynge. Outwardely we ſe the prieſte, outwardely we heare this ſentence, Take, eate, this is my body,<note place="margin">Augu. ad infantes.</note> &amp;c. pronounced by the prieſt, outwardely we ſe the formes of breade and wyne, and theſe are as perceptible and eaſy to be perceaued of the Turkes &amp; other Infydels, as of vs Chryſten men, that is, they ſe and heare as much, and the very ſame, touchynge theſe outwarde thynges, that we do: But then is there the inuyſible prieſt, who bad the viſible prieſt do this, and that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth and worketh by him, as by his inſtrument, and the effecte and operacion of theſe wordes, take, eate, this is my body, which is to change thoſe viſible creatures into the ſubſtaunce (as Emyſen, Chryſoſtome,<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. de p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de</note> ſaynte Ambroſe, and ſuch lyke autours do wytneſſe) of Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bleſſed body and blood, where is further to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydred that the very naturall body and blood of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uioure Ieſu Chryſt to be conteyned vnder, and ſigny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by thoſe formes of bread and wyne. Chryſte hym ſelfe is a moſte true wytneſſe, and beſte to be beleued herein; who alſo ſayth, that it to be the ſame bodye that was broken for vs, and the ſame blood that was ſhedde for vs. And theſe thynges good people that is the inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſpeaker and worker, the effecte or workynge of theſe wordes, and the moſt precious body and blood of our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſt, theſe thynges I ſay are the priuities &amp; ſecretes the which are not to be ſene of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels
<pb facs="tcp:5395:7"/>and Turkes, and yet beleued of Chriſten men and conceaued by fayth only: For who beinge an Infidell, wolde thynke that God were in his prieſte, ſpeakynge or ſaying to vs, take, &amp; eate, this is my body? Or who being voyde of fayth, wolde thinke that there were any thynge done, by the vertue of theſe wordes, take, eate, this is my body, more then is done by theſe: Chryſt is the ſonne of God, and ſuch lyke, the which do not worke any thyng, that is, do not make Chryſte to be the ſonne of God, but teacheth that he is the ſonne of god: Who I ſay beinge an infidell, wolde not thinke an operaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and effecte, to be of both theſe, that is, to teache, and not to worke any thynge? And then bycauſe that it is moſte certeyne, that breade is not his body, muſte they ſay eyther that Chryſt ſayde not trewe, or els muſt they expounde it, to be a figure of his body. Thus I ſay, an Iufidell or a faythleſſe man, can haue no other vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge of theſe wordes, which doth both worke and teache (for that is the nature of the wordes that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyneth to a ſacrament, to teache and worke bothe) then he hath of other wordes, whoſe office is onely to teache. Nowe iudge you then, whether our newe goſpellers, be men voyde of fayth or not. They ſay the ſame effect to be of theſe wordes, this is my body, and of theſe, I am a vyne ſo that as Chryſt was not a vyne, but figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the vine, ſo doth not theſe wordes this is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, chaunge the ſubſtaunce of the breade and wyne, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chryſtes body and blood, but teachethe that they be fygures of his body and blood, the whiche thynge once graunted, ſe I pray you what foloweth, then muſte ye
<pb facs="tcp:5395:7"/>confeſſe alſo that the lyke vnderſtandynge, muſte be of theſe wordes of baptiſme, I baptize thee in the name of the father and of the ſonne and of the holy ghoſte and then it muſt folowe, that as theſe wordes do importe that to be Chryſtes body, which is but the figure of his body, ſo doth the prieſt ſay in baptiſme, that he baptiſeth you, when in dede he geueth to you but the fygure of your baptiſme, and ſo ye neyther eate Chryſtes fleſhe, nor yet be Chryſtened in dede: Are not theſe cunninge workemen in diuinitie trowe ye, that ſayth like as theſe wordes, I am the vine, are to be vnderſtande, the vine is a fygure of me, ſo this is my body, muſt be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, this is a fygure of my body, and ſo muſt the prieſt ſay, I do not baptiſe the, but do gyue the a figure of the baptiſme, and then ſeinge that al the ſcriptures that be contrary to reaſon, muſt be ſo expounded, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> agree with reaſon, ſo muſt this ſayinge of the Father, this is my welbeloued ſonne, be vnderſtande that this is a fygure of my ſonne bycauſe it is ageynſte reaſon, that a man ſhulde be gods ſonne, and ſo wyl they make our ſauiour Chryſt not to be the ſonne of god. Iudge you good people, whether this be a pretty diuinitie or not: Secondely yf ye wyll ſay that to be breade, which Chryſt ſayth to be his body, or that to be a figure of bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, which Chryſt ſayth to be baptiſme it ſelfe. What haue ye I pray you to proue eyther that ye do eate it, or that ye be baptiſed, ye feyne a ſpirituall eatynge, where haue ye that in ſcrypture, and take the effecte of theſe wordes away but to let this. Thyrdely howe I pray you be the bread and wyne (which do ſignifie in eating)
<pb facs="tcp:5395:8"/>figures of Chryſtes body and blood, if his body be not in deede eaten? But as I ſayde, an Infidell can not knowe, that as the holy ghoſt, was vnder the forme of a doue, ſo is heare the bodye of ourſauioure vnder the forme of bread: An Infidell lokynge uppon the viſible forme of breade, knoweth that there is a thyng to be ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten: but only a Chryſtian man knoweth what it is that is eaten, for he is taught of Chryſt that it is his bleſſed body. Thus I ſay, ought we that be beleuers, to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and iudge them as myſteries of our fayth, and they be therfore myſteries, bycauſe one thynge doth appere in them outwardely, and they be inwardely another, as ſaynt Auſtyne wryteth to the infantes, that to the iudgement of theyr ſences, there is breade and wyne, but to the knowledge of oure faythe, they be Chryſtes moſt precious body and bloud. Nowe theſe hauynge as I ſay, two partes, the one knowen to our ſences, the other to our faith, it is nowe then to be conſidered wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>upon and by what grounde our fayth muſte be ſtayed, and that all men knoweth to be Gods worde: for that ſaith our ſauiour is ſo ſewer,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that thoughe heauen and earth paſſe away, yet ſhal that continue. Wyll ye ſe then what this worde ſayth?<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>3.</hi> Iohn. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> The worde ſayth, that Adam was poyſoned with eatynge of an apple, and Chryſte ſayth, that his fleſhe is ſo neceſſary a triakle to dryue out this poyſon, that except we eate his fleſhe, and drynke his blood, we ſhall not haue lyfe, the which thinge once graunted, what ayleth vs that we can not ſee to ley the playſter to our ſore? That is lyke as bothe our bodyes and ſowles were poyſoned with the apple, ſo muſt both
<pb facs="tcp:5395:8"/>our bodyes and ſowles be reſtored by Chryſtes fleſhe eaten of vs, and as not a figure of an apple, but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry apple was eaten, ſo not a figure of Chryſtes body, but his very bodye is to be eaten, for to reſtore ageyne our nature. Moreouer Gods worde ſayth, that as we haue the ſubſtaunce of our bodyes from Adam, ſo haue we our corruption and ſinfulneſſe with the ſame. And our ſeconde Adam ſayth, that except we come into him, and be made one with hym by eatyng of his fleſhe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Roma.</hi> 5. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.</note> that we ſhall not eſcape death, for he that eateth his fleſhe, and drynketh his blood, abydeth in Chryſte, and hathe Chryſte abydynge in hym, whereby we be taught that as we haue not in vs a fygure of Adam, but the very ſubſtaunce of Adam, and not his ſubſtaunce onely, but his ſubſtaunce and his ſinne, ſo muſt we haue in vs like wyſe, not the fygure, nor the ryghteouſnes onely of Chryſtes body, but his very and natural body in dede. Furthermore the Iewes had Manna,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>16.</hi> Exod. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> and theyr Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call lambe, the whiche were figures of Chryſte, of the whiche Manna dyd ſignifie Chryſtes incarnacion, in that as Manna was created in the pure ayer, or as it is called in the ſcripture heauen, by Gods omnipotent power, and not by the order of nature, ſo was Chryſtes body in the pure and heauenly wombe of the virgin, be yonde or aboue nature, created by the holy ghoſte, and as Manna fell downe and laye vppon the grounde, ſo was his precious body ſlayne and layde in graue: &amp; as Manna was gathered vp and eaten, ſo dyd it ſygnyfie that the ſame body of our ſauiour ſhulde alſo be eaten. The Paſcall lambe alſo dyd ſignifie the humanitie of
<pb facs="tcp:5395:9"/>Chryſte, that as the lambe was without ſpotte, ſo was Chriſt conceaued without ſinne, and as the lambe was ſlayne, ſo was alſo Chryſte, and as the ſame lambes fleſhe was eaten, ſo dyd it ſignifie that Chryſtes fleſhe ſhulde be eaten: And thereupon ſayth ſaynt. Bede and ſaint Ierome,<note place="margin">In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men tarus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Luke et ſuper Math.</note> that Chriſt went from the fygure, to the truth, when after the Paſcall lambe beinge eaten, he conſecrate this bleſſed ſacrament. And ſe heare I pray you good people, howe that our newe profeſſoures of our late ſpronge fayth, doth make by theyr doctrine, the ſcriptures to be falſe: for theſe figures that I haue reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, doth ſo well teache the eatynge of Chryſtes fleſhe, as eyther his incarnacion, or death, and therfore if the promeſſe that was made by the fygure, be performed in the two fyrſt poyntes, not figuratyuely, but really, &amp; doth ſo wel ſignifie the thyrde, that is the real eatyng of his fleſhe, ſhal not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled eyther to ſay that the Iewes did not eate Manna, nor the Paſcal la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be in dede, but figures of them, or els to ſay that the promiſes of Chriſtes incarnacion &amp; paſſion, were trewe &amp; be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, &amp; that the thyrde, which is of his fleſhe to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, was eyther falſe, or that it is yet to be performed, but then ye wyll ſay, that we eate his fleſhe ſpiritually, and dyd not they the ſame I praye you, when they eate Manna, and the fleſhe of the Lambe? And howe then is there any promyſe made to them which is performed to vs, ſeinge we haue no more then they had? ye do you marke and yf they make not vs to be in worſe caſe then the Iewes were. For they had Manna, and a Lambe, and we haue common breade and wyne, the which who
<pb facs="tcp:5395:9"/>knoweth not to be much leſſe worth, then were Manna and the Lambe: for as I ſayde they dyd remember Chryſtes death, and were parteners of the fruites ther of, for theyr tyme and portion, ſo well as we be. And thus do they make the newe teſtamente and the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes therof, to be worſe then the olde. It ſhall not be nedefull for me to reſite vnto you the ſayinges of our ſauiour Chryſte in al the foure Euangelyſtes, and in ſaynt Paule. For ye knowe in them all Chryſte ſayth, eyther that his fleſhe is very meate, and therefore vere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be eaten, or els, take, eate, this is my body whiche is geuen for you: In no place nameth he it eyther to ſignifie or to be a figure of his body: ye do alſo beare in mynde,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 24.</note> that as Moyſes toke the cup whrein the blood of ſacryfyce was, and ſayde that it was the blood of the Teſtament:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 22.</note> ſo dyd Chryſte take the Challes wherein was the bleſſed blood, being the blood of our ſacryfyce, &amp; ſayd that it was the cuppe of the newe teſtament, that is lyke as we be certeyne there to be the blood of hym that dyed for the performaunce of the newe teſtamente, ſo myght we be ſuer, that all that was ſayde, or ſpoken vpon in the teſtament, ſhulde be performed. Colde this be done thinke you, ſo conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly with a cuppe of wine? But nowe to here what the holy fathers haue beleued in this matter, I pray you marke.<note place="margin">De cena.</note> Saynt Ciprian the glorious martyr, and an aunciente father beinge nere thyrtene hundreth yeres agone, doth not he ſay that the breade which Chryſt gaue to his diſciples kept ſtyll the ſame ſhape that it had, and yet by the omnipotencye of Gods worde, it was chaunged in nature &amp; was made
<pb facs="tcp:5395:10"/>Chryſtes fleſhe. Euſebits Emiſen an auncient father almoſt twelue hundreth yeres old, ſayth, that the inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible prieſte turneth the viſible creatures into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce of Chryſtes body and blood. Saynt Ambroſe more then .xi. hundreth yere olde, ſayth, that before the wordes of conſecration the Chaleſſe is ful of wyne and of water, but after the wordes, there is the blood that redemed the people. Saynt Auguſtine beinge of the ſame tyme ſayth, that in his tyme they did not iudge the ſame of the thynges in the ſacramente before the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration and after, for before they dyd acknowledge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be breade and wyne, the which nature had made, but after they profeſſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be the body and blood of oure ſauiour, which grace had conſecrated, &amp; the ſame ſaynt Auſten doth alſo ſay, that as the perſon of our ſauyour dyd ſtande of his viſible manhod, and his inuiſible god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed, ſo ſayth he doth the ſacrafyce of the Churche ſtand pon the viſible formes of breade and wyne, and of the inuiſible fleſhe of our ſauiour Ieſu Chryſte. To theſe myght be added Chryſoſtome, ſaynt Ierome, Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſene, Theophilacte &amp; many other, ye al Chryſtendome do wytneſſe the ſame: wherefore you beinge faythfull men and women, that do in theſe myſteries of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe remoue your vnderſtandynge frome the thynges that ye perceaue by your ſences, as frome the prieſte or the ſounde of the wordes, the viſible formes of breade and wyne, vnto God the autour of them, the workyng of the holy ghoſt by the wordes, and the body and blood of our ſauiour: Graffe theſe thynges deepely in your hart, and practyſe them in your iyuynge, adherynge to
<pb facs="tcp:5395:10"/>the fayth and religion of his catholyke Churche, ſurely and ſtedfaſtely beleuyng, that vnder theſe formes of of breade &amp; wine here in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the aulter there are conteyned really the bleſſed body and blood of oure ſauyour Chryſt. And yf ye thus do, ye ſhal pleaſe and ſerue God, profyte your ſelfe and your neyghbour, with the hole congregacion, and lyuynge well accordynge to Chryſtes commaundementes, ſhall haue for your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the bliſful kyngedome of heauen: which graunt vnto you the father, the ſonne, and the holy ghoſt, three perſons and one God, to whom be all honoure, prayſe, and glory, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <head>¶ Of the Sacryfice of the Maſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here be three thinges (good people) wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal men be moued to ſeke lernyng and knowledge, that is the truth which is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally deſyred of all men, the profyte that men get by knowledge, and the pryce or goodneſſe of the thynge that we deſyre to knowe, by the which cauſes, as men be moued to deſyre knowledge, ſo are theſe cauſes no where more forceable and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely to be conſidered then they be in the ſacryfyce of the maſſe, the which is dayly vſed in the Church. For fyrſt it is not vnknowen to you, what ſtryfe there hath byn about it, and howe that lerned men of both partes haue
<pb facs="tcp:5395:11"/>ſpent theyr lyues in the controuerſy therof. Secondely ye ſe that bycauſe it is proued or improued by the name of a ſacryfyce, it muſt nedes be a thynge that appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſo to vs all that it deuydeth one parte of ſuche as ſtryue about it vtterly from God. For yf the maſſe be a ſacryfyce to god in deede, then it maketh thoſe that be meinteyners &amp; the vſers of it to be better beloued with god then other. For a ſacryfyce is as much to ſay, as an holy worke, and therfore ſeing that god loueth the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers of holy thynges, ſo muſt he loue them that ſerueth hym at or by the ſacryfyce, &amp; then alſo are ſuch as ſtriue ageynſt it, the moſt enemies that god hath. For they labour to kepe that worke vndone wherein he is beſte pleaſed. And yf contrarywyſe it be no ſacryfyce, then be they wronge worſhyppers of god that vſe the ſacryfice, which is as much to ſaye, as that they be ſuperſticious Idolaters. And for the excellency of the thynge, what I pray you can be compared in excellency with this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce? which is as much to ſay as the moſte ſacred or holy worke that can be. For in offeringe of the ſacryfice we be moſt heuenly or lyke vnto the bleſſed company of heauen, whiche are continually occupyed in worſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge and honorynge of God. Theſe cauſes moſt dere brethrene and ſyſtren hath cauſed me that hath the cure vpon your ſoules (ſeinge ye be by reaſon of theſe diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of doctrine brought into ſuche daunger) to teache you what is ment dy this worde ſacryfyce, and that ye may knowe the better how we do differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Iewes to ſpeke of the diuerſitie of the ſacryfyces, and to ſpeake alſo howe the maſſe is in dede a ſacryfyce. And verely
<pb facs="tcp:5395:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>(good people) the ſame cauſes that moueth me to teach you, ought to moue you to lerne, for ye may of this that I haue ſayde ſe what danger ye be in, yf ye be ignorant in this ſo great a matter. The which thinge that ye may the better vnderſtande, I fyrſt note vnto you that there be, and alwayes haue byn three principall partes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ioyned together, and one folowynge vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. That is the teſtamentes or couenantes that God maketh with man, the prieſthod or office of ſuch as god hath made myniſters of his teſtamentes, and the ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce or worke wherin the people do recognyſe and moſt faythfully acknowledge the ſame couenauntes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge whereunto ſayth ſaynt Paule that <hi>Omnis ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fex ex hominibus aſſumptus, pro hominibus conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itur in iis quae ſunt ad deum vt offer at dona et ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia pro peccatis.</hi> That is, euery byſhop taken forth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amongſte men, is appoynted for men to be occupyed in thoſe thynges that do apperteine vnto god, that he may offer gyftes and ſacryfyces for ſinne. In which wordes are to be ſene the three thynges that I ſpake of before, that is, fyrſt the teſtament by the which the byſhop muſt be choſen (for no man ſayth ſaynt Paule may vſurpe ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour to hymſelfe) ſeconde the byſhop who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaint Paule ſayth to be a miniſter of thoſe thynges that be betwixte man &amp; god, and the thyrde is the ſacryfice, which alſo he ſo nameth. Thus (good people) was there a teſtament or a couenaunt made betwyxte God and the people of Iſraell and Aron, as ye knowe was choſen to be a my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the ſame teſtament, and as ye knowe his my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſtery was alſo in offerynge of ſacryfyce. Chryſt alſo
<pb facs="tcp:5395:12"/>was a miniſter of the newe teſtament, and dyd alſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſacryfyce as ye knowe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hebre.</hi> 10.</note> and nowe good people if the ſame teſtament that was begon by Chryſt doth ſtyl con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue, and ſhall vnto the worldes ende, than lyke as Arons ſacryfyce, teſtamente, and prieſtehod begonne together and continued together vnto Chryſtes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge, and were all abrogated together at one tyme by Chryſte. Euen ſo moſte deare brethren, yf we wyll that Chryſtes teſtament ſhall continue amongſt vs, ſo muſt we alſo haue his prieſthod and ſacryfyce. Heare then may we ſe the malious wickednes of the deuyll, in all our miſerable heretickes that denye both the prieſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hod and the ſacryfyce of the newe teſtament the which thynge yf he or they colde brynge to paſſe, then myght we ſay that there is no teſtament neyther. For it was ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſene nor harde before, that euer there was a teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without theſe. Secondely it is contrary to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the ſcripture, the which as ye ſe ioyneth the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the prieſthod, &amp; the ſacryfyce together. Thyrdely it is contrary to ſaynt Paule, who ſayth that the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was to be chaunged, and not to be taken away by Chryſte, but what other is it to chaunge it, but to put a better in the ſtede thereof?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hedre.</hi> 7.</note> Wherefore as the olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was by Chryſt chaunged into a better, ſo muſt it folowe that he dyd not take away the prieſthod and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, but chaunged them into a better and a more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte prieſthod and ſacryfyce. And what prieſthod from ye and ſacryfyce dyd he chaunge them into? Verely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the prieſthod and ſacryfyce foreſhewed longe before by the prieſthod and ſacryfyce of Melchiſedech accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bene.</hi> 14 <hi>Hebre.</hi> 7.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5395:12"/>as the prophet Dauyd had ſpoken of Chryſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſayinge,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.</note> 
               <hi>Tu es ſacerdos in eternum ſecundum or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem Melchiſedech.</hi> Thou art a prieſte for euer accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge vnto the order of Melchiſedech But what was the order of Melchiſedech? Certeynely ſaythe ſaynte Paule he was a fygure of Chryſte, what I praye you was his ſacryfyce? Verely ſayth the ſcrypture breade and wine, the which were likewiſe figures of Chriſtes bleſſed body &amp; blood, that is nowe dayly offered vnder the formes of breade and wyne, in the tyme of this teſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mente, for as Melchiſedechs prieſtehod was a fygure of Chryſtes, ſo was his ſacryfyce a figure of Chryſtes ſacryfyce. Witneſſes haue I for me in this matter ſaint Auguſtine in dyuers places, and namely in his booke intyteled <hi>De Ciuitate dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. de Ciuitate dei. lib. <hi>16</hi> Capi. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> there he ſaythe that when Melchiſedeth dyd bleſſe Abram then dyd fyrſte apeare the ſacryfyce the which Chryſten men do offer through the whole worlde, and the thynge is nowe fulfylled that was ſpoken vpon Chryſte ſo longe before. Marke ye good people howe he ſpeketh, he ſayth, not that it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was, but that it dyd then apeare. Ye knowe that there is a great diuerſitie betwyxt the beinge of a thyng, and the appearynge of it, for the thynge may appeare by his fygure, as by the materiall breade that Melchiſedech dyd offer appeared the heauenly breade, that is Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes owne bleſſed body, whiche he dyd in dede offer at hys ſupper, and is dayly offered in the Church, as ſaint Auguſtin before reſited, doth moſte playnely teſtyfye. The ſame figure of Melchiſedech and his ſacryfyce is thus applyed by ſaynt Ierome, ſaynt Bede, and other
<pb facs="tcp:5395:13"/>dyuers holy fathers, whoſe doctrine (moſt dere fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des) it ſhalbe muche more ſure and holſome to folowe then the doctrine of our maried prieſtes,<note place="margin">Iero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ad marcel Ambro li. <hi>5</hi> de ſacra. ci</note> who maketh al this buſineſſe ageynſt the bleſſed ſacrament &amp; ſacryfyce, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that theſe being made nothyng worth, they might without reprofe lyue fleſhely. But to returne ageyne vnto our purpoſe: The thynges beinge as I haue told you, and it ſo playnely taught to vs by the ſcryptures it is to wyt that theſe three, the teſtament, the prieſthod, and the ſacryfyce be alway ſo ioyntly together, that the one of them is neuer founde without the other, that is, neyther the teſtament without the prieſthod and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce, nor they without the teſtament. It requyreth in order that we do ſay briefely what theſe be, and howe they do agree together. And concernyng the fyrſt, that is the teſtamente, ye ſhall vnderſtande (good people) though we call the bookes wherein the lawe of God is conteyned the teſtamentes, yet in dede they be but as it were tables or ſcrolles wherein the explication or the playne declaration of the teſtamentes be conteyned, for what man is ſo fonde that thynketh the olde teſtamente to haue begon at Moyſes, who was in dede but the wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter of the olde teſtament? Or is there any ſo ignorante of our religion that thynketh the newe teſtamente to haue begonne at the Euangeliſtes, and not at Chryſte, whome we do well knowe to haue made perfecte his teſtament or euer any of the Euangeliſtes dyd wryte. Mary ye ſhall vnderſtande that the ſame that we call the teſtamente,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ge.</hi> 9.17. <hi>Ieremi.</hi> 31</note> doth God almyghty call <hi>Pactum,</hi> that is his couenauntes or agrementes with vs, and oures
<pb facs="tcp:5395:13"/>with hym. The couenauntes &amp; ye lyſte to knowe when they were made, and with what wordes they were vtte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, ye ſhall vnderſtande that the fyrſt and elder teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was made betwyxt God almyghty &amp; Adam our fyrſt father in paradyce,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 3.</note> which was that Adam beinge a man nowe caſt forth of Gods fauour, and by his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruynge moſte iuſtly adiudged vnto death, ſhulde be reconcyled to gods fauour and reſtored to lyfe ageyne by the appoynted ſede of the woman which was our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour Ieſu Chryſt, by whom the ſerpentes heade (by which is vnderſtande the power &amp; ryght that the fiende had ouer man) ſhulde be broken, ſo that Adam &amp; thoſe that ſhulde come of Adam, wolde faythfully wayte for the commynge of our ſauiour, and in the meane ſeaſon labour to do god ſeruice, ſo nere as mans frayltie wold ſuffer them. Nowe wot ye well good people, that this agrement was very pleaſaunt and ioyful vnto Adam, and all thoſe that were faythfull were very gladde that they ſhulde be reſtored ageine vnto theyr fyrſt dignitie, the which they had loſt by diſobedience. And herein as it were to beate wytneſſe betwyxt god and man of this agrement, there were choſen prieſtes, the which at the beginninge whyles the lawe of nature did raigne were choſen of the chiefeſt and heades of the people, and ſo was Noe for his houſhold, and Abraham for his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde, and Melchiſedeth kynge of Salym a prieſt for his whole kyngedome.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 8. <hi>Gene.</hi> 12. <hi>Gene.</hi> 14. <hi>Gene.</hi> 22. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.</note> Afterwardes when the people began to forget gods couenantes, and the chiefe of the people began to mynde the worde more then god, then God cauſed Moyſes to publyſhe his teſtamente in
<pb facs="tcp:5395:14"/>wrytynge, and dyd then choſe out the ſtocke of Leuy to be his prieſtes vntyll that teſtament that was made to Adam in Paradyce ſhulde be chaunged.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke.</hi> 2. <hi>Mark.</hi> 17</note> And to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that they ſhulde the better mynde God, and ſet the leſſe by the worlde, he appoynted them to lyue by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyces whiche were offered vnto hym.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibi.</hi> 18.</note> Theſe then (that is) bothe the prieſtes that were vnder the lawe of nature, and vnder the lawe of Moyſes, dyd offer the ſacryfice of the people vnto god, that is, they in theyr of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce doynge, were wytneſſes betwyxt god and the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, that he was the god that had made the promeſſe, &amp; that theſe were the people that dyd faythfully truſt and loke for the ſame to be performed.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leuiti.</hi> 9.</note> The whiche that it myght be the better perceaued and more faythfully borne in theyr remembrance,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leui.</hi> 19.</note> he toke ſome lyuely thing and ſlewe it in theyr ſyght, that they ſeinge the thynge that had not deſerued ſo to be ordered, to be burnte and conſumed in theyr ſyght, might the better conſider how they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues had deſerued thus to be ordered, that is, to be burned, ſlayne &amp; conſumed, but yet that almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty god had tranſlated the death from them, and layde it vpon our ſauyour Chryſt, who hauynge no cauſe of death in hym ſelfe, no more then the innocente lambes had,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſei.</hi> 53.</note> yet ſhulde be ſlayne for them. Nowe ſe I pray you and if they had not the moſt innocent death of our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, euen as it were expreſſed and ſet before theyr eyes, when they dyd thus preſently beholde the ſlaughter of thoſe beaſtes. Do not you thynke the ſyght and behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of thoſe ſacryfices though they were but figures dyd better cauſe them to remember Chryſtes deathe,
<pb facs="tcp:5395:14"/>then yf they ſhuld haue hard of it in the wordes or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynge of prieſtes? Nowe then yeſe what the teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the prieſthod, and the ſacryfyce be, it is alſo nowe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that ye knowe howe many teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes there be, and howe they do dyffer. Fyrſt for the nomber of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ye knowe that they be two, the one made of God vnto man in Paradyce,<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>3.</hi> Math. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> the other made of god vnto man at the baptyſynge of our ſauyour Chryſt. In the one, god promyſed that the ſede of the woman ſhulde breake the ſerpentes heade: In the other he ſayde, this is my well beloued ſonne in whom I am well pleaſed, heare hym, the which is as much as yf he had ſayde, this is the ſede that breaketh the ſerpentes heade, I that was angrye with you before, am nowe fully reconſyled vnto you, nowe I requyre no more of you, but that ye wyll be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his diligent and ſaythfull ſcholers. Theſe twoo teſtamentes as ye ſe do dyffer in theſe poyntes: Fyrſt, that the fyrſt dyd teache a promeſſe, this teacheth a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formaunce. The fyrſt had his perferte ende at Chriſtes death and paſſion, the ſeconde had his abſolute and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fecte beginnynge at the ſame, and therefore calleth the ſcrypture out ſauyour Chryſt the corner ſtone, as one ſhulde ſay a ſtone in whom the two walles, that is the two teſtamentes were cowpled together.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>117</hi> Math. <hi>21.</hi> Eph. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> For Chryſte in his death, was bothe a prieſte accordynge to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Aron bicauſe he was offered with bloodſheding whiche was the maner of ſacryfyſynge in the order or prieſtehod of Aron,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciuitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. liber. <hi>20.</hi> La. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> and he was alſo in the ſame paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a prieſt of the newe teſtament, in ſo much as that he dyd offer hym ſelfe, for that by the doctrine of ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>guſtine
<pb facs="tcp:5395:15"/>is proper to the ſacryfyce of the Churche. For Chryſt ſayth, that beinge bothe the prieſte that offered, and the ſacryfyce that was offered, taught his Churche both to offer and to be offered at once, his wordes be theſe. <hi>Per hoc et ſacerdos eſt ipſe, offerens ipſe, et ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio cuius rei ſacramentum quotidianum voluit eſſe eccleſiae ſacrificiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quae cum ipſius capitis corpus ſit ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſam per ipſum diſcit offerre.</hi> That is: In ſuche ſorte was Chryſt a prieſt, that he both offered the ſacryfyce, and was the ſacryfyce, of the which his doynge, he wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the ſacryfyce that is dayly vſed in the Churche, to be a Sacrament, the which Churche beinge his body, and he the heade of the Church, the Church hath nowe learned to offer her ſelfe by hym, by the whiche he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that as Chryſt in his paſſion dyd both offer, and was offered, ſo doth the deuoute people at the maſſe in a certeyne reſpecte both offer the body of Chryſte vnto God, and when they offer it, they do offer vp the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues. For lyke as the headde and the bodye maketh but one thynge, ſo the body of our ſauyour Chryſte, wherewith the Church is dayly fedde, being heade of the Church, and the Churche that eateth the ſame bodye beinge ſo made one with Chryſt, that it is his body, ſo whan the Church doth offer his body in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the Church doth offer her ſelfe, for ſhe offereth her heade. For (moſt Chryſtian hearers) ye ſhall vnderſtande that as the thynge that is eaten,<note place="margin">Cirill. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. ca. <hi>17</hi> libro. <hi>11.</hi> C. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> and the thynge that eateth, are by eatynge made one, ſo by eatynge Chryſtes bleſſed body we be made (as ſayth Ciryll) really and corporally one with him, not that we diſgeſt him, but that he diſgeſteth
<pb facs="tcp:5395:15"/>vs, and thereupon are we called members of Chryſte,<note place="margin">Locus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectione digniſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> and he in dede is our heade, &amp; by the ſame reaſon, when we offer<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp hym, we offer our ſelues, this thynge good Chryſtian people is harde to be vnderſtanded, and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where fayth wanteth, and the vertue of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſacrament is vnknowen. But to returne vnto our purpoſe, this may be added to the diuerſities of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyces of the olde and newe teſtament, that the olde were ordeyned by men that were mynyſters, this by Chryſte, eyther in hym ſelfe, or in his members to be done. Furthermore concernynge the newe teſtament, ye knowe it to be the agrement made betwyxt Godde and vs,<note place="margin">Ecce an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuncio vobis gaudium magnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c Luke. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and therefore is the doctrine therof called <hi>Euan gelium,</hi> as one ſhulde ſay good tydynges. For it was a ioyfull thynge to heare that man is reconcyled to Gods fauour ageyne. Alſo concernynge the miniſters of this teſtament, there is no dout but that the Apoſtles, the Diſciples, and ſuch as be choſen in the Church for that purpoſe, be miniſters of this teſtamente. Mary nowe all the controuerſie that is amongſt vs at this preſent, is whether they be to be called prieſtes or not, and that is alſo for bycauſe that certeyne euyll diſpoſed perſons, ſayth that we haue no ſacryfice: Howe be it, as I ſaid theſe go ſo together, prieſtood, ſacryfyce, and teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that yf ye take away the ſacryfyce, ye muſte alſo denye the prieſthod, and ſo conſequently the teſtamente alſo. Wherefore to teache that there is a prieſthod, we muſte fyrſt proue that we haue a ſacryfyce, the whiche is eaſy to be done yf ye wyll but call vnto your remembraunce that the ſacryfyce is nothynge els but a dede or a worke
<pb facs="tcp:5395:16"/>which expreſſeth the couenaunt that god hath made vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to man, and that we that be the doers eyther in acte or in conſent, be ſuch as acknowledgeth the teſtament or couenaunt to be made vnto vs. Nowe then marke I pray you but what the couenant of god is to vs, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is accomplyſhed and fulfylled, and what deede or worke doth moſt perfectly repreſente or ſhewe it to the congregation of the faythfull. For the teſtament, was it not that we ſhulde heare Chryſte his ſonne, and that then he wolde be pleaſed and at one ageyne with vs? For the tyme when this agremente was fully accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyſhed and made, who doubteth but that it was then, when our ſauyour ſuffered his moſt hytter paſſion for vs vpon the croſſe?<note place="margin">Collo. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> For as ſaynt Paule ſayth, the blood of Chryſtes croſſe made a generall peace betwyxt God and al his creatures that be eyther in heuen or in earth. Alſo for to repreſent this agrement, both howe it was made, and when it was made, what I praye you can better repreſent or ſhewe it, then the conſecration of the bleſſed ſacrament in the remembraunce of his moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious death and paſſyon? When the prieſt appoynted to conſecrate thoſe bleſſed myſteries, callynge vnto hym the aſſyſtaunce of the holy ghoſte (as ſaynte Denyce ſayth) and reſytynge the ſame wordes that Chryſt our ſauyour ſpake and wylled to be continually ſpoken in the celebration of theſe moſte bleſſed myſteries.<note place="margin">Dioniſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us cherar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtica.</note> And when by the vertue of the ſame wordes, and the holy ghoſte workynge by theym, the breade is turned into Chryſtes moſt ſacred body, and the wine into his moſt precious blood, is not then the couenaunte of God, the
<pb facs="tcp:5395:16"/>death of Chriſt, &amp; the maner of his death expreſſed vnto you? whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by your reſortinge to heare maſſe ye cauſe the prieſt to conſecrets this bleſſed ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and he accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to his office, fyrſt conſecrateth the hoſt, and after ſheweth you the body &amp; blood of our ſauyoure couered with the formes of breade &amp; wyne, (bycauſe theſe miſte ries ought not to be ſene but of you that be faithful) whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſaye you do nowe as it were with your eyes ſe hym there, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was ſaide, here him &amp; I am pleaſed,<note place="margin">Eum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des cum tanges Chriſoſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad po. ho. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye ſe the ſame body that was ſlayne, couered there vnder the fourme of breade, &amp; the blood that was ſhed to be there vnder the fourme of wyne, do not you then proteſt that ye be the people to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe couenauntes were made, &amp; that Chriſt dyed for your re de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ption, and that his death was not by hanging, drownyng, or ſtran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelyng, where the blood is conteyued within the body beinge deade, but that his death was by ſheedynge, or deuydynge of his bleſſed fleſhe and blood in ſunder? Thus haue ye by the celebration of this bleſſed ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment theſe thre thynges euen as it were ſet before your eyes to be conſidered, fyrſt that Chryſt dyed for you, the cauſe why he dyed for you, and the maner howe he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for you, &amp; thinke you not this worke then (good peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple) to be moſt worthy to be called a ſacrifice that expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſo playnely to vs theſe neceſſary poyntes of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? Or do ye thinke that any worke of man may be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared with this, not onely for that it was inſtitute &amp; ordeyned of god, but for that god who made the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; we to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the teſtament is made, do here at the celebracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theſe bleſſed miſteries mete together, he to
<pb facs="tcp:5395:17"/>performe and make good his promeſſe, and we to aſke the benefite of the ſame, the bleſſed body of our ſauitour beinge as it were a pledge or toke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> betwyxte God and vs, that is, that he made the promeſſe, and that we do nowe ryghtfully craue it.<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. de euche to. <hi>3.</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile ad monitoria</note> Accordynge whereunto ſaith Chryſoſtome, good Lorde the table is prepared with the myſteries, and the lambe of God is offered for the, and the prieſte prayethe for thee, and the ſpirituall blood is there flowynge vpon the holy table, and the Seraphins ſtande rounde about ſhadowynge his face with theyr wynges, and al the incorporal powers pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth then with the priſt for thee, and as foloweth a lyttle after, art not thou then ſayth he aſhamed? art thou not afrayde? yea art not thou vtterly confounded,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de tempore ho. <hi>251.</hi>
               </note> that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge this opportunitie wylt not labour to gette Gods mercy and fauour? Alſo in lyke maner doth ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine charge his dioceners with commynge to ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce, and eſpecially vpon the ſondayes vnto maſſe, and there he ſayth, that men ought of dutye to come vnto the Church vpon the ſondayes and other holy dayes to all the ſeruyce, and yf any man be letted by neceſſarye buſineſſe, that he can not come to the Churche, yet he ought to pray at home, but he ſayth that without any ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſe he ought vpon the holy day deuoutly to here maſſe, and blameth certeyne very ſharpely that do not ſo. For he ſayth. <hi>Adhuc quod deteſta bilius eſt, quidam ad eccle ſiam venientes, non intrant, non intendunt precibus, non expectant cum ſilencio ſanctarum miſſarum cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brationem.</hi> That is, yea this is much more deteſtable, certeyne when they come vnto the Church, eyther they
<pb facs="tcp:5395:17"/>wyll not go in, or they wyll not gyue them ſelues vnto prayer, or they wyll not with ſcylence abyde vntyll the maſſes be celebrated and ended. Thus may ye ſe good people, what theſe holye fathers dyd iudge vppon the maſſe, the which our newe brethrene hath taught you to reuyle and diſpyſe. But then ye wyll aſke me what ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures teacheth the maſſe to be a ſacryfyce. And verely amongſt many more then the tyme wyll ſuffer me to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyte, theſe do teache it. Fyrſt the ſacryfyce of the Paſcal lambe the which our ſauyour did change at his ſupper, and placed in ſtede thereof this ſacryfyce of his bleſſed body and blood, and that the Paſcall lambe was a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice the ſcripture is playne For ſay the not the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture playnely, that all the Iſraelites ſhulde offer vp the Paſcall lambe at the euen tyde? and ſaythe not ſaynte Paule that Chryſt was offered vp a paſſouer.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 11. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> The which wordes declareth that the Paſcall lambe was a ſacryfyce. Wherfore as the newe teſtament commynge in place of the olde, is by right called a teſtament, ſo this commynge in ſtede of the ſacryfyce, is iuſtly named a ſacryfyce. For as theyr paſſouer put them in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce howe they were deliuered forth of Egypte, ſo doth this put vs to remember our delyueraunce out of hell: wherefore it is moſt playnely to be ſene, that this is the ſacryfyce of the Churche. For this is a good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that it ſhulde be a ſacryfyce, bycauſe it commeth in place of a ſacryfyce.<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>14.</hi> Pſal. <hi>109.</hi> Hebre. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> Secondely the ſcripture that ſaith Melchiſedech to haue byn a fygure in his prieſtehod, of our ſauyour Chryſtes prieſthod, teacheth this to be a ſacryfyce. For onely in the inſtitucion of theſe bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:5395:18"/>myſteries dyd Chryſt fulfyll the thynge that was figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Melchiſedech, that is, as Melchiſedech offered vp materiall breade, ſo dyd Chryſt offer this heauenly breade that is his owne bleſſed body vnder the fourme of breade. Thyrdely the propheſy of Malachy teacheth it,<note place="margin">Malla. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> where he ſayth that the gentyles ſhall offer vnto god a newe and a moſt cleane ſacryfyce. But why ſhulde not this be called a ſacryfyce beinge the ſacryfyce of the newe teſtament, and what thynge in cleaneneſſe can be compared with the precious body and blood of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyour Chryſt? Fourthly the wordes of our ſauyours Chryſt, ſayinge do this in my remembraunce, teacheth that it is a ſacryfyce,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 22. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> for as thoſe workes and thynges were called ſacryfyces, that dyd ſygnyfye his deathe to come, ſo by the ſame reaſon ſhulde this be a ſacryfyce, that declareth it to be paſt.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.</note> Fyftly ſaynte Paule when he to dryue away Chryſten men frome the ſacryfyces done vnto the Idols, nameth the cup of our lord, what other dothe he, but ſaye that this is the ſacryfyce that Chriſten men onely haue? And ſo comparynge our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce and theyrs together, ſayth, that they coulde not drynke of the cuppe of our Lorde, and of the cuppe of deuyls. But then ye wyll ſay, howe can this be a ſacry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce, ſeinge that it is commonly called a ſacrramente. Verely (good people) it is called a ſacrament or a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, for that it appeare the to the Infydels to be one thynge, and is knowen of vs to be another as to them it apereth to be nothyng but breade, but we knowe that it is Chryſtes body in the fourme of breade, and of this ſecrete or pryuie beinge heare, it is called a ſacrament.
<pb facs="tcp:5395:18"/>It is alſo called a ſacryfyce for that the prieſte doth conſecrate them to repreſente the deathe and paſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſauyour Chryſte, ſo that there be two vſes (good people) of theſe myſteryes, the one to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, wherof Chryſt ſpeaketh ſayinge. Take, eate, this is my body, the other is to put vs in mynde of his death, wherof he ſayth, do this in remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of me. In the fyrſte vſe it is a ſacramente, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde a ſacryfyce. But then ye wyll ſaye ageyne that the celebracion of theſe myſteries co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſacrynge, is but one parte of the maſſe, truth it is, that the ſacryfyce whiche Chryſte lefte to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in his Church, is in dede but that part whiche we commonly call the ſacrynge, and as for the other partes, they be eyther prayers or ceremonies wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſacryfyce is bewtyfyed and commended, euen as a mans body is bewtyfied with comely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell. But yet as the clothes be one, that maketh the body comely, &amp; the bodye that is made comely with them, is another, and the bodye is better then the apparell, ſo be the cerimonies and the ſacryfyce dyuers in the maſſe, thoughe we call them bothe by one name. And as the kynges perſon is but one, whether he be in his dublet and hoſe, or in his cote, or in his gowne, or in his robes, ſo is the celebracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe bleſſed meſteryes the offerynge of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce, with what kynde of ceremonyes ſo euer they be mynyſtred, ſo that there be nothynge lefte out that Chryſte dyd ordeyne.<note place="margin">Platiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de viris ponti.</note> And thus do we rede that ſaynte Peter ſayde maſſe at Antyoche,
<pb facs="tcp:5395:19"/>and vſed no mo cerymonyes nor prayers at his maſſe, but the Pater noſter. Mary no man may chaunge or leaue forthe the ceremonyes, bycauſe that obedyence is to be ſhewed, and an vnyformy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is to be obſerued, and ſlaunder is to be auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Thus then haue I ſhewed you what a ſacry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce is,<note place="margin">Hie cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitas miſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> videli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet chri. Baſil et ceterorum non in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificio ſed ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cii cerimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis.</note> and howe it is always ioyned with the teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, and prieſthod, what dyuerſities there be of teſtaments, and ſacryfyces, and howe the maſſe is a ſacryfyce repreſentynge the death of our ſauyour, and the body and blood of our ſauyour beinge pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto God by vs, is called an oblacyon, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the prieſte whom we cauſe there to conſecrate or ſay maſſe, ſetteth them as pledges betwyxte God and vs, to wytneſſe that he by theym is made oure God, and we by them are made his people, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſacryfyce yf we do faythfully beleue and duely mynyſter, ſhall euermore preſerue, contynue, and increaſe the loue and amytie that is made by Chryſt our ſauyour, betwixt almyghty God and vs, to whom be honoure and prayſe, nowe and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:19"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:20"/>
            <head>¶ Of fayth and knowledge of God.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>VAni ſunt omnes homines in quibus non ſubeſt ſelen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tia dei</hi> (that is) All the men be but vayne that wante the knowlege of god, theſe wordes of the wiſe man (good people) howe trewe they be, it ſhal be eaſely ſene, yf we do conſider the great &amp; depe wyttes of the Phyloſophers, to what vanitie they were brought, for that they wanted the trewe knowledge of god. This I ſay their confuſion doth wel apere to thoſe that readeth theyr workes, &amp; ſerch with what vaine queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; diſputacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s theyr braines &amp; heads were occupied: yea it ſhall appere playnely to al thoſe that do but rede the fyrſt chapter of ſaint Paul to the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. Greate kynges &amp; noble men for want of this knowledge,<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> haue ſodeinly come vnto confuſion and ſhame, the whiche thing is to be ſene not onely in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of whom we rede in the ſcriptures, &amp; other bokes of hiſtories, but the erperie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that we haue of certeine vngodli perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in this our time doth moſt plainely ſet it before our eyes. Do ye not ſe that not only Golias: but that al vngodly perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s howe ſtronge ſo euer they be, be moſte ſone confounded by his or theyr ſtrengthes? Where or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ye ſene but that the ſtoute me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſtrongeſt, or as they be called maſters of fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, haue bin more ſhamefully confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded then the weaker or febler me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea howe ſeldome do ye ſe that ſuch lacke wounded or maimes? &amp; how fewe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dieth peaceably in theyr beds, who knoweth not that the rich man is al his lyfe troubled in the getting, keping, &amp; beſtowynge of his rycheſſe &amp; yet is not onely rebbed of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ofttymes ſlayne for his ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſſe: To be briefe, al ſtates of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be vaine beinge voyde of this knowledge. For as the earth and the worlde ſhuld be altogether out of frame, yf they were not dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly dight &amp; ordered by the bodely labour of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; as ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s body could do nothing but lye ſtil as a blocke, corrupt
<pb facs="tcp:5395:20"/>and ſtynke, yf it be deſtitute or forſaken of the ſowle: ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſowle of man beinge deuyded from God, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> or not knowynge God, can do nothynge but hurte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe, and brynge both the body whereunto ſhe is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>te or ioyned, and all the thynges that the body med <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with, out of order, wherof commeth all the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and miſerie that is in this worlde. Wherfore good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>le, yf ye wolde be rydde out of this vanitie, yf ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>de lyue welthely, yf ye wolde lyue as men agreable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> nature of man: then can there be nothynge ſo ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt to you, as the knowledge of God, ſo muche deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or wyſhed of you as the knowledge of god. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>th all the rycheſſe, dignities, or wyſedomes in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lde, no ryches, no principalitie, no cunnynge or ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge can be compared to this. For what other ſcience where that teacheth ſuch thynges as this dothe, that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſay, which teacheth what god is, what the Angels be, that the ſowle of man is, yea that teacheth heauen and he ioyes therof, hell and the paynes therof, the worlde and the ryght orderynge or vſe thereof. And what ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers are more happy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they that do lerne theſe thinges and what other ſcience can make the ſcolers &amp; learners her of moſt rychely and euerlaſtyngely to lyue in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen but this: yf men were perfectly inſtructe and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in this, then ſhulde men ſtande leſſenede of al other ſences, and yet ſhulde thynges muche better floryſhe and proſper with vs then they do. For howe lyttle wold the vſe of ſubtyll and craftye artes auayle, yf all men through this knowledge were adicte, bent, and gyuen vnto ſimplicitie? Howe lyttle nede ſhulde men haue of
<pb facs="tcp:5395:21"/>phiſicke yf death did rather pleaſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then life, ſickenes and health, lyke pleaſaunt and greuous? The regarde of lawe ſhulde be ſmall yf men were perſuaded rather to ſuffer, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do wronge. To be ſhort, yf this facultie and ſcience were truly planted in mens hartes, all miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries ſhulde ceaſe, and all plenty of happynes ſhulde be increaſed. But alas in this our miſerable time, through our prating &amp; diſputing of this knowlege: what heapes of errors &amp; hereſies are ſpronge in or about this facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or knowledge: this out knowledge, which is fayth, is vtterly decayde amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt vs, for as ſaint Paule ſayth, <hi>Qui vult accedere ad deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hebre. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>primo oportet credere deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe</hi> that is, that he which wyll come to God, muſte come by fayth.<note place="margin">Auguſtin ſuper.</note> And ſaint Auguſtine ſayth <hi>Non currendo, ſed cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do peruenimus ad deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> that is, we muſt come vnto god not by running but by beliefe, this fayth or knowledge good people, being ſo neceſſary, &amp; yet amongſt vs ſo pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly decayed, I ſhall exhort you as ye do tender the health both of your bodyes &amp; ſowles, that you prepare your ſelues moſt earneſtly to lerne it, for without it both you &amp; al that you haue are but vaine: And as this is of al ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces the chiefeſt, ſo it requyreth ſcolers that ſhalbe moſte laborious and diligent, to the intent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that this heuenly knowlege may be the better opened vnto you, I wyll ſhewe you fyrſt what fayth is, then howe faythe muſt be vſed, and then howe it muſte be defended, that we do not erre or be deceaued therein. Fyrſt then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernynge the definition of fayth: ye ſhall vnderſtande that ſaynt Paule defineth it to be an argumente of the thynges that we hope for, and the ſubſtaunce of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:5395:21"/>thynges that do not apeare: that is to ſay,<note place="margin">Hebre. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> fayth is the cauſe why we truſtinge in the promyſes of God, are con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tent to beare all aduerſitie, to do all dueties, hopynge thereby to be rewarded of God. And alſo fayth is the ſtay or aſſuredneſſe which we haue of, and concerninge the thynges that can not be comprehended by our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. As for example, the knowledge which we haue of God, his Angels, and of heauen: Alſo of the deuyll, hell, and the paynes that be there, lykewyſe of oure ſowles, and theyr immortalnes, &amp; to vſe fewe wordes, eyther of the beginnynge, the rewle, gouernaunce, or endynge of the world. Fayth, I ſay is the very ground and foundacion whereuppon all mans knowledge is buylded, in the contemplacion of all theſe ſo greate and weyghty matters, ſo that no man beynge of hym ſelfe able to knowe theſe thynges, muſt lerne them of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that doth not vnperfectely knowe theſe thynges, &amp; that is iuſt, honeſt, &amp; trewe that man may ſafely &amp; with out daunger beleue and credyte, the partie teachynge theſe thynges to hym, the which matter (that is) the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte of thynges vnknowen, that it maye be the better perceaued, I ſhall deſyre you to marke three thynges, which be theſe. Fyrſte who is the reporter, what be the thynges that are reported and what they muſte be to whom this report is made. For the fyrſt, it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne that God is only the reporter, or ſome ſuch as are purpoſely ſent of hym, to make the report accordyng as we rede god to haue reported to Adam &amp; Eue in Para<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dice, the great miſerie that they ſhuld be in,<note place="margin">Gent. <hi>3.</hi> I. bide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> if they ſhuld eate of the apple. And after theyr faule, he reported
<pb facs="tcp:5395:22"/>both theyr redemption and the deuyls confuſion, which was after wrought by our ſauyoure Chryſte. Alſo he reported to Cain that Abels blood cryed vnto God for vengeaunce.<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>4.</hi> Gene. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Vnto Noyhe reported that Gods iuſtyce was prouoked to punyſhe the world for ſinne, and that he yet and his houſholde ſhulde be ſaued in an Arke, to Abraham he made report why the cities were to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>18.</hi> Gene. <hi>22.</hi> Math. <hi>4.</hi> Math. <hi>3.</hi> Math. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> and howe that all people ſhulde be bleſſed in his ſeede, and bycauſe I wolde not be longe, dyd not our ſauyour beinge God preache the goſpel? &amp; dyd not the father report that Chriſt was his derely beloued ſo, did not our ſauiour ſay,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> that it ſhuld not be his Apoſtles that ſhuld ſpeke, but the ſpirite of our father that ſhuld ſpeke in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, doth not ſaynt Paule ſay <hi>Legatione dei fun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gimur apud vos,</hi> that is, we be gods ambaſſadours, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you do not all the prophetes ſaye <hi>Hec dicet dominus,</hi> thus ſayth our Lord, of the which al &amp; many mo textes that myght be gathered, it doth moſt euidently apeare that god is the reporter, or ſuch as be ſent from hym, of all thoſe thynges that Chryſten men ought to beleue: and here is to be noted good people, fyrſt the mercifull goodnes of god, who doth ſo voucheſafe to teache ſuch ſory and wretched creatures. Secondely, howe happy be we that haue ſuch a maſter. Thyrdly, howe ſafe and holſome are thoſe leſſon which we lerne of him, the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che thynge yf we dyd pythely conſyder: O howe they wolde make oure ſtonye hartes to melte: O howe myndefull ſhulde we be aboute theſe leſſons: O howe lyttle wolde we regarde then all the other thynges that be, or myght be taught vnto vs, eyther by the worlde,
<pb facs="tcp:5395:22"/>the fleſſhe, or the deuyll, touchynge the thynges which he teacheth, they be ſtyll manifeſte, and are alwayes in a redineſſe to be ſene, and lerned in his worde and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore doth his worde remayne, bycauſe that the thinges that he reporteth myght be alwayes in a redineſſe,<note place="margin">John. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men ſhulde or wolde learne and knowe theym: of the which wordes and thynges ſome were ſpoken and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported before the tyme of our redemption, and ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the time of our redemption. Before the tyme was the creacion of man, the fall of man, promyſes of man, reparinge, and ordinaunces to prepare and ieade man towardes his redemption, the which all had byn moſte incredible yf any other ſhulde haue reported them but God. Howe be it, nowe when we ſe the thynges ſo to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to paſſe as it was reported that they ſhuld, nowe is it euidente howe trewe he is that made the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte, touchynge the thynges that were taught at the tyme or about the tyme of our redemption, they were ſo ioyfull that the reportynge of them was called the goſpel, as one ſhulde ſay, glad tydynges. As the Angel ſayde, lo I ſhewe to you great ioy that you haue a ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our borne: for wot you well good people,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> that this was a ioyfull tydynges to all the faythfull that knewe howe they had byn longe deuyded from God, and hadde byn thrall and captyue to the deuyl,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> to heare that nowe they ſhulde be deliuered from the clawes of the foule fiende, and brought in the fauour of theyr fyrſt &amp; trewe maſter owner and maker. Ageyne this I ſaye my dere bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren (conſidered) I meane the thraldome that they were in, &amp; the ioyful libertie that they ſhulde be reſtored
<pb facs="tcp:5395:23"/>vnto, made the faythfull hartes to reioyce, concerning the thynges that be reported in the goſpell,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>2</hi> Iohn. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> ſome prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vs towardes god, as penaunce, other be of ſuche ſorte, that by them God taketh vs to hym, and geueth his grace to vs, the which thynges bycauſe they be ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall tokens of his fauour towardes vs, and our obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entneſſe to hym, therefore they be called ſacramentes, as one ſhulde ſay pryuie tokens of his fatherly loue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs, for there be no louers, but they wyll haue ſome thynges ſo priuie to themſelues, that other ſhall not knowe them, and theſe in Greeke be called myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in Latin ſometyme <hi>Arcana,</hi> and ſometyme <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menta,</hi> in Englyſhe, ſecretes or priuities. Thus we be in the water of baptiſme, but waſhed in our body, to the ſyght of the vnfaythfull, but in that knowledge &amp; ſyght that we haue, we knowe that we be ſo waſhed in oure ſowle that we be made newe creatures. Alſo in confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation we be but vncted with the holy oyle, and to the ſyght of the faythleſſe be but vncted: for the faythleſſe do terme it ſmurrynge, in the reproche of the bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but we knowe that then we receaue the grace of the holy ghoſt, which ſoupleth our ſowles to reſiſt the deuyll, and to obey gods commaundementes, as oyle cauſeth our bodyes to be ſoupple and nimble, both to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde the thynges that be euyll, and to do thynges that be good. In the moſte bleſſed ſacramente of the aulter the faythleſſe thynketh that we do eate breade: but we knowe that it is the precious body of our ſauiour which was gyuen for vs, and the ſame is to be conſydered in the reſidue of the ſacramentes. There be other thinges
<pb facs="tcp:5395:23"/>that be reported to vs when we thus (as I haue ſayde) are receaued and admytted vnto God, of the whiche, ſome do belonge to our duties to be done, and ſome be promyſes or thynges promyſed to vs for doinge of our duties, as the reſurrection of our bodyes, and increaſe of our ioyes in heauen. Theſe thynges (good people) when I do conſyder, I am conſtrayned to crye out, and alas that euer our hartes ſhulde be ſo bewitched to regarde golde and ſyluer, yea meate, drynke, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell ſo much, and theſe ſo lyttle: alas what compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion is there betwixt thoſe, and theſe? but ageyne nowe to the ſcholers, who ſeith not howe obedient they ſhulde be to ſuche a maſter: O howe ought we to obeye hym with all the power of our ſowles, with all the ſences and partes of our bodyes, with all oure goodes and worldely ſubſtaunce. Thus our father Abram dyd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey when he left his countrey, his acquaintaunce, and rycheſſe, and ſought them agayne there where god had apoynted. Alſo thus dyd he ſubdue his reaſon and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (which ſayde that he and his wyfe beinge old, ſhuld haue no chylde) vnto God reportynge that he ſhulde haue one. Alſo the Centurion whoſe fayth was ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended of our ſauyoure, that the lyke was not to be founde in all Iſraell.<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Howe I ſay dyd he ſubdue bothe his ſence and reaſon, to the wyll and pleaſure of God, when ſence and reaſon ſayde that Chryſte muſte of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie come into his houſe, or els his chylde coulde not be healed, and yet he aunſwered that it was ſufficiente for Chryſte to ſpeake the worde, and in his abſence to heale the chylde.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>8.</hi> Math. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> In lyke maner dyd ſaynt Peter ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due
<pb facs="tcp:5395:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>his reaſon and ſences to the reporte of God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſayinge by our ſauioure, this is my welbeloued ſonne. &amp;c. Or els if he ſhulde haue byn taught by fleſhe and blood as the Iewes were, he ſhulde haue knowen Chryſt onely to haue be the ſonne of our Lady and Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph, as the Iewes dyd. Furthermore at the tyme whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chryſt ſayde vnto his diſciples, and to the Iewes, that his bleſſed fleſhe was to be eaten,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 6.</note> then dyd the Iewes prefer reaſon before the report of our ſauyoure, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of theyr reaſon and ſences, howe that myght be trewe: and bycauſe reaſon and ſences teache no truthe therof, therfore dyd they depart and go theyr way, but the bleſſed Apoſtles who gaue more to Chryſte then to theyr ſences, and ſubdued theyr reaſon and ſences vnto the ſayinge of our ſauyour, and dyd ſay, <hi>Verba vi ta eterna habes,</hi> that is to ſay, thou haſt the wordes of euerlaſtynge lyfe, as one ſhulde ſay, thoughe we by our ſences and reaſon, do not knowe howe thy fleſhe muſte be eaten (for then the inſtitution of the bleſſed ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was to them vnknowen) yet be we moſte ſure that thy worde can not be but trewe. Alſo ſaynte Paule ſayth, <hi>Corde creditur ad iuſtitiam ore aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> confeſſio ſit ad ſa lutem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 10.</note> And therfore we may not examine what reaſon and ſences ſayth in thoſe matters that be taught to vs of God, but we muſt with an obedient hart beleue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and howe folyſhe ſo euer they apere to oure reaſon and ſences, yet we muſt not be aſhamed openly to confeſſe them.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.</note> Here we maye conſyder nowe howe harde a thynge it is to be a true ſtudent or ſcholer of fayth. For lyke as our youth is loth to leaue their ſenſual pleaſure
<pb facs="tcp:5395:24"/>and to obeye the inſtructions of theyr elders, that they myght learne cunnynge and knowledge: ſo harde is it for vs that be fleſhely, to forſake our reaſon and ſences, and to imbrace with al humilitie and obedience,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge and leſſon of almyghty God. Ageyne here is to be ſene what reuerence they that be faythful do gyue vnto god, that ſo offer them ſelues vnto god, that they wyll ſuffer them ſelues not to be taught any further by theyr reaſon, or any other creature, then they ſe them to agre with god, and of him they do and wyll learne, thoughe he teache thynges, the whiche apere to the iudgemente of all other to be moſt vntrue. We alſo may ſe here howe al faithleſſe people, &amp; eſpecially heretickes do blaſpheme god, which geueth more credyt to theyr reaſon, ſences, and other experience, then they do vnto god: I meane that he ſpeakynge of the bleſſed ſacrament, ſayth it to be his bodye, and reaſon, ſence, and experience, that it is breade. Theſe I ſay that rather folowe the iudgement of theſe creatures, then the report of god, do make that they be more honeſt, iuſt, and true, then god, the which howe blaſphemous it is, iudge you. Nowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to come vnto the ſeconde parte of our purpoſe (that is to teache the vſe of our faythe) that is verye well declared in the fyrſt article of our Crede, where we ſay that we beleue in god the father, and ſo forth: the whiche is as ſaynte Auguſtine ſayth, thorowe fayth ſo to cleaue vnto god, that we knowe hym to be ſo neceſſarye a helper, that without hym we can do nothynge that good is.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 15.</note> For as the braunche is deade and fruteleſſe, except it remayne in the vine: ſo be we voyde of al fruteful vertues except
<pb facs="tcp:5395:25"/>his grace do worke in vs. In ſo muche that as ſaynte Paule ſayth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</note> no man can ſay Ieſus to be our Lord, but by the holy ghoſt, this is our wekeneſſe, and the onely helpe of god is in dede a remedy to the ſame, the which was ſo well knowen to the prophet Dauyd, that he let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not to ſay vnto God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.</note> thou (ſayth he) haſt holden me by the ryght hande, and in thy good wyll haſte thou led me. Accordynge to the ſame ſayth ſaynt Paule, that he coulde not thynke one good thought of him ſelfe:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.</note> but al his ſufficiencie was of God. Saynt Peter in lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner conſideringe howe needefull it was thus thorowe fayth to be ioyned vnto god,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Petri.</hi> 2.</note> byddeth that we ſhulde be as chyldren that were newe borne, deſyryng that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, and that is voyde of crafte and deceyte, in the which exhortacion of ſaint Peter (moſt dere brethrene) callynge vs by the name of chryldren that be lately borne, is moſt plainely declared and ſet before our eyes what it is to beleue in god, which is ſayth he, to behaue our ſelfe towardes god, as ſuckynge babyes do behaue them ſelues towardes theyr parentes, in the which it is not onely to be ſene, that as the parentes be neceſſarye for the chyldren, whyles they be yet infantes: ſo is god to vs, but it expreſſethe three eſpeciall properties that ſhuld be in vs, as be in the infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, which be theſe. Firſt ſo to beleue his parentes, that the infante knoweth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, neyther can he call any thynge by any other name then his parentes do teache him, in ſo much that yf the parentes wolde teache their infantes that a ſhepe were to be called an oxe, and a horſe a ſhepe &amp; ſo forth, chaunge the name of the thynges, and not ſuffer the
<pb facs="tcp:5395:25"/>childe to here them called by any other names, the child I ſaye wolde call all the thynges by the ſame names that he hereth his parentes call them by: The lyke ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie (good Chryſten people) was in all good men, and ſhulde be in vs that be faythfull. For this we ſe to haue byn in ſaint Paule,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> in ſo much that he knewe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge, after or accordynge to the fleſhe, whiche was as much as yf he had ſayde that he hadde changed his knowledge, from the teachynge of his ſences, vnto the teachynge of our heauenly father almighty God, where vnto he moueth vs, in that he biddeth vs to be renewed in the ſence of our vnderſtandynge.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ephe.</hi> 4.</note> This ſimplicitie (deare brethrene) if it were in vs, wolde we reaſon and diſpute of gods myſteries as we do? if we had our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces taught of, or by god, wolde we be ſo proude and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſumptuous, ſo ſubtyll and ſo crafty? No no, wot you well we wolde not: We ſay we beleue in god, but haue we this fyrſt poynt which is chyldyſhe ſimplicitie, and much leſſe then haue we the reſidue. The ſeconde is, that as chyldren vſeth in theyr infancy neyther to bye or craue for the thynge that they lacke or want of theyr pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes, &amp; at theyr handes do receaue the ſame thinges: ſo ſhulde we do that be Chryſten men. For we ſhulde ſay with the prophet Dauyd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>Tu es qui extraxiſti me de ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre matris mee, ſpes mea ab vberibus matris mee, in te periect us ſum ex vtero,</hi> that is. Thou art he that taketh me forth of the wombe, and euen from my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pappes hath my truſte bin in thee, and frome the wombe was I caſt vnto thee, and for the lyke purpoſe
<pb facs="tcp:5395:26"/>(that is, that we ſhulde craue vpon hym as chyldren do at or of theyr parentes) he ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 16.</note> verely I ſay vnto you, what ſo euer thynge ye ſhall aſke of my father in my name, he wyll gyue it to you, alſo aſke and ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue, ſeke and ye ſhall fynde. &amp;c. Further to encorage vs the rather to aſke as chyldren,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 7.</note> of oure heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he ſheweth howe redy he is to heare, and to giue the thynges to vs that we aſke, ſayinge, whiche of you beinge demaunded of his childe to gyue breade to his chyld, wyl giue a ſtone? &amp; ſo according that our heuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly father wyl much ſoner then any carnall father, gyue the thynges to vs that be neceſſarye for vs. Here then may we lerne good brethren, fyrſt our dignitie, whiche is, that we wretches be admytted by prayer not only to ſpeke with god, but alſo that he wyll graunte our ſutes and requeſtes. O howe bleſſed an eſtate is this? O the comfort that is thus in prayer to be ſought &amp; found? A poore begger that can not be ſuffered to ſpeke with a temporal prince ſhalbe ſo eaſely admytted to ſpeke with hym that is the prince of all princes: and by promyſes after a certeyne maner hyred ſo to do. Is not our colde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in prayer worthy to be condempned? and we that wyll not craue are we not worthy to faſt. Secondely, here is to be ſene howe careleſſe and quyet we might be ſeinge that we maye haue all thynges for the aſkynge. Howe happely myght we be folowynge the councell of the prophet Dauyd,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 54.</note> to caſt all our care vpon God, that he may noriſhe vs, then what ſhulde nede our ſolicitude and carefulneſſe? what ſhulde then nede our craft and diſſimulation, and ſuch lyke. The thyrde is, howe hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb facs="tcp:5395:26"/>ſome myght theſe thynges be trowe you that are gyuen to vs of this wyſe and louynge father? And contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe howe daungerous and perylous be the thynges that be geuen to vs by the deuyll of couetouſnes, by the deuyll of flattery, or of ambition or ſuche lyke? frome the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (derely beloued) commeth our robbryes, our mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders, our treaſons and ſuch lyke, that our ryches, and our promotions are not gyuen to vs of our father, but of the fiende, and therefore as the fiende dyd kyll the ſowle of him to whom he gaue them: ſo is it his paſtime and pleaſure to kyll and murther other mo by takynge the ſame away ageyne. Let vs then aſke of our father, and refuſe to take ought at the deuyl. The thyrd thinge that is in chyldren, and that muſte be in vs that beleue in God, is louynge obedience, that is, as good children to obey theyr parentes rather for loue, then for feare: ſo ſhulde we obey god.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14.</note> Whereunto our ſauyour ſemeth to moue vs, when he ſayth, yf ye loue me kepe my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes. Se here the louyngenes of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father, who moueth not for feare of punyſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but for naturall loue and pitie due vnto ſuche a father, moueth vs to our dutie, and yet thoughe he do chiefely moue vs to obſerue and kepe his commaundementes thorowe loue: yet bicauſe he ſeeth vs to be ſlacke to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſider it, he addeth alſo ſome toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of loue. Alſo of feare, ſayinge yf I be your father, where is my honoure and reuerence: yf I be your maſter, where is my feare:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mala.</hi> 1.</note> thus he exhorteth the wyllynge and obediente for loue, and the ſtubberne for feare of punyſhement. But woo vnto vs at this tyme, whome nother loue nor yet feare
<pb facs="tcp:5395:27"/>can cauſe to be obedient. Whatſore plages hath God caſt vpon this realme? and howe hath he taken awaye ſometyme our corne, our graſſe: and yet wyl we rather that oure ſhepe and beaſe ſhulde dye for hunger, then we wyll diminiſhe the pryſes of them. Sometyme he deſtroyeth our corne and cattell bothe: and yet rather then we wyll relent and obey hym, we wyll make that one ſtryke of corne ſhalbe better then ten, and oneſhepe or beaſt ſhalbe worth fyſtene. Is this my brethrene to beleue? is this to beleue in god? is this the token of one that wyll be reformed by god? or is it not rather the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of one that wolde fyght with god: but conſyder, O conſyder you that do fyght ageynſte hym, that you can not (I ſay) preuayle ageynſt him. Remember the dred<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful day of iudgement, when ye rebellious childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt apere before hym. Here then maye you ſe that to beleue in god is fyrſt: that as ſimple children do knowe no per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon but hym and all thynges by hym. The ſeconde is, that as the chylde hangeth altogether vpon the prouy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his parentes, and ſheweth his nedes to theym: the like muſt we do to hym in whom we do beleue. The thyrde, as the chylde is ruled by his parentes chiefely of loue, and where that wanteth, for feare of punyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: in lyke maner muſt they do that beleue in God. The thyrde thynge that is to be obſerued in our fayth, is that we take hede and beware that the deuyl our ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mie do not deceaue vs, as he dyd oure mother Eue in paradyce,<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and as he deceaued all the people whome he cauſed in the tyme of nature, and of the lawe, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt Idolatry, and as he after in the tyme of grace hath
<pb facs="tcp:5395:27"/>cauſed no ſmal number of ſuch as hath borne the name of Chryſten men, to be heretickes, And therefore byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſaynte Paule,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> the Corinthians to take heede that they be not deceaued by the deuyll, whoſe miſcheuous thoughtes and imaginacions was not vnknowen, ney<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to the bleſſed Apoſtles, nor yet to the Corinthians. And Chryſt our ſauyour in ſundry places byddeth vs to beware of hym, and of his malycyous meſſengers, And ſaynte Peter telleth vs before, that as there were falſe prophetes in the tyme of the lawe:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pe.</hi> 2.</note> that ſo there ſhulde be teachers of falſe and damnable ſectes in the tyme of the Goſpell. And we knowe by experience that there hath byn thouſandes ſence he gaue vs warnynge to take hede of them, and to eſchewe them, the whiche holſome monicion gyuen vnto vs by our ſauyour, and by his bleſſed Apoſtles, and we ſeinge that ſuch as did not regarde theyr monition, haue moſte damnably fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into hereſy and blaſphemous vanities. O howe ear neſtly and effectuouſly ſhuld they cauſe vs to be afrayd and to beware what ſpirite it is that we gyue credyte vnto. Is there any bodye ſo deſperate in his bodely health, that when he heareth his phyſytion ſay, drynke not of this for it is poyſon, and that ſeith before his eyes men that dyd drynke thereof to be poyſoned, that wyll yet without all reſpectes to be had, other to his phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that monyſſhe the hym, or to the man who he ſeethe deade with the poyſon, drunke therof? And alacke I ſay, ought not our ſowles to be more dere to vs, then is the body of a man to any man: but howe then thynke you that we beinge but as babyes, and Gods ſuckynge
<pb facs="tcp:5395:28"/>chyldren, can be able to auoyde ſuche cruell daunger of that miſcheuous beaſte the deuyll? Verely if ye lyſte to knowe it: other wayes is there none, then to keepe vs within the houſe of our father, which is the Catholike Church. For the keper of this houſe is ſo ſtronge, that it is vnpoſſible that there ſhuld come any ſtronger that ſhalbe able to ouercome hym,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> and to ſpoyle his houſe. This houſe is builte vppon the rocke that all the gates and power of hell can not preuayle ageynſte it.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> They that remayne in this houſe,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14. 1. <hi>Timo.</hi> 3.</note> are ſo ſuer not to be decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with any damnable error, that they haue the ſpirite of all truth to theyr ſcholemaſter, this houſe is fre from error and heriticall blyndnes, that ſaynt Paule calleth it the pyller and the ſtay of truth. The doctrine of this ſchole hath byn ſo liefe and dere to al the good men that hath byn, and yet be, that euery man ſaythe that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth the Catholyke Churche, and that euery man is bounde in the peine of dampnation, to reteyne and kepe the Catholyke fayth. &amp;c. Howe be it the deuyll our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mye ceaſſeth not to perſwade men to thynke, that this howſe of god is onely frequented and occupyed of and by them that be good. For God (as he wolde them to thynke) wyll ſuffer no vnthryftes to be in his houſe, and ſo conſequently he wolde make vs to forgette, and to be ignoraunt of this our fathers houſe, bycauſe we do not knowe in what parte of the worlde that ſuch good men do dwell.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> But (good people) ſaynt Paule teacheth the contrary to this: ſayinge that it is a greate houſe, and that there be in it veſſels both of honour and diſhonour. And our ſauiour ſayth,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> that it is lyke to a net that catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:5395:28"/>both good fyſhes and bad, the which ſhalbe ſuffered to continue together vntyl it ſhalbe giuen in commaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dement to the Angels at the ende of the worlde, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde the euyll from the good: ſo that this doubt aboue mencioned, is nothynge els but a craft and a ſleyght of our goſtly enemie the deuyll, vſed to the intent and pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe, that we myght (as I ſayde) forget to knowe and deſerne our fathers houſe. But that the deuyll lyethe, and that it is knowen: Marke thou good Chryſten man and woman, that Chryſt our maſter ſayth it to be buylded as a citie vpon a hyll, that can not be hyd, and he biddeth that for the redreſſe of ſuch matters as be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyxt thy neyghbour &amp; the,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that thou ſhuldeſt apeale to the church,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> &amp; there thou muſt (in peyne to be caſt clene out of his fauour) obey and abyde the determinacion of the Church, the which were altogether ſpoken in vaine yf the Church coulde not be knowen. Wherfore by this that I haue ſayde, ye may ſe moſt dearely beloued, firſt the danger that we be in, and howe that to auoyde the ſame we muſt kepe vs in the houſe of our father, which is the Churche. Ye ſe howe craftely the deuyll goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with his falſe and miſcheuous flattery, to hyde the houſe from you, that you ſhulde not knowe it: howe be it, yf the deuyll ſhulde ſet vp a thouſande houſes, as he hath ſette vp manye alredy, to reſemble ſo our fathers houſe, that we ſhulde not be able to deſerne it from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet ſhal I ſhewe you howe, and in what maner ye ſhal be able at al times to deſerne our fathers houſe and his inſunder. Fyrſte ye ſhall vnderſtande that the houſe of our father was fyrſt built, &amp; that the deuils buildinges
<pb facs="tcp:5395:29"/>be but counterfeite and forged to ſome ſimilitude of our fathers houſe: wherfore as the thynge muſte be before the ſimilitude of the thynge, ſo muſt the houſe of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be of more antique, and auncient buyldynge, then the deuyls houſe, or houſes that be made to ſome ſimy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, or ſhape of our fathers houſes, and therefore ſayth Tertuliam ageynſt the heretickes that be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyls wryghtes to buylde his houſe.<note place="margin">Tertulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti.</note> That muſte be the trewth which was fyrſt, and that muſte be falſe whiche is the latter. And thus dyd Dauyd ſaye that he knewe which was the faythfull people of God, and what reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion did pleaſe God.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>77.</hi> Deu. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> For he hath harde it with his eares and that his fathers tolde hym. Alſo in his booke of the lawe, god biddeth vs to aſke of our fathers, &amp; that they ſhall tell vs, and our auncytoures, and that they ſhall ſhewe to vs gods true religion.<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Alſo our ſauyour in the goſpell callynge vs by the name of ſhepe, ſayth that his ſhepe doth knowe the voyce of theyr paſtor or ſhepard, and that they flee and run away when they here a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, which is as much to ſaye, that the trewe Chryſten men muſt kepe and reteyne ſuch doctrine as they haue byn accuſtomed vnto, and that they muſte eſchewe the doctrine that is newely and lately ſpronge.<note place="margin">Ephe. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Alſo ſaynt Paule byddeth vs that we do not as chyldren that are led away with euery blaſt of doctrine.<note place="margin">Auguſtine contra fu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>damentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> macheoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> C. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Moreouer then this, ſaynt Auguſtine ſayth that he wold not beleue the goſpell, but that the autoritie of the Church dyd moue hym, and in very dede by good reaſon. For howe ſhuld we otherwyſe be able to ſaye that this is ſaynte Iohns goſpell, or that ſaynte Lukes goſpell ſhulde rather be
<pb facs="tcp:5395:29"/>receaued, then the goſpell of Nicodemus or of ſaynte Thomas and other, but that we be ſo taught by the Churche. Alſo ſeinge that the Churche whiche is gods houſe hath contynued this. <hi>1556.</hi> yeres, and was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer caſte yet downe: we maye be ſure it to be the houſe that is buylt as Chryſt ſayth vpon the rocke. The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d argumente or token to knowe the Churche by, is the greatneſſe and largeneſſe of the ſame. For the houſes of the fiende belyttle pretty feate houſes, buylded but in corners of the worlde, as it myght be in Englande, in Germanie, and ſo forth: but our fathers houſe is ſo am<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple and large,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>106</hi> Pſal. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> that it reacheth frome the ryſynge of the ſonne to the goynge downe of the ſame. For as the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prophet Dauyd dyd propheſie of it, before the voyces of his bleſſed Apoſtles, whoſe diligence he dyd vſe in buyldinge of his houſe,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> went thorowe the whole world, and the ſame prophet ſayth, that the earthe, the worlde, and all that is in them, belongeth vnto our Lorde and maſter Chriſt, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſent forth his workmen to buyld his houſe, he dyd not ſende them into Englande onely, or into Germany only:<note place="margin">Mark. <hi>16</hi>
               </note> but bad them go into the whole worlde and preache the goſpell. And ſaynt Paule doth moſte ſharpely rebuke the Corinthians for that they ſuffered the deuyll to begyn his buyldynge with them,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> and therfore he byddeth them conſyder yf the worde of god went no farther but to them, and remayned only with them, doynge them to vnderſtande thereby, that they ſhulde not ſuffer them ſelues to be deuyded frome the reſidue of the worlde, that had receaued and kepte the goſpell ſo well as they dyd, and accordynge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto
<pb facs="tcp:5395:30"/>vnto ſayth ſaynt Auguſtine, as we knowe by Goddes worde where Paradyce was planted:<note place="margin">Auguſt. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tra petil. liber. <hi>2.</hi> Capi. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> ſo do we knowe by the ſame, where the Church is, that is amongſt all nations, hauynge her beginninge at Ieruſalem, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we be monyſhed of the ſtrength of our father, who hath ſubdued the whole worlde to his obedience. For he ſayth, in euery corner of the world ſome there be that be his. Alſo we may ſe the wekenes of the deuyll, who in buyldynge of his hereſies is ſo weke, that he lyke a chiefe ſtarteth vp nowe in this corner of the worlde, and nowe in that, or as it were a prince with his army of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belles, or apoſtatas that forſaketh theyr religion, doth what he can to withſtande the army of Chryſt, in ſome parte or portion of Chryſtes dominion. But as rebels be eftſones brought to theyr confuſion, ſo hath alwayes his armies frome tyme to tyme byn confounded and brought to naught. And yet further, as rebellions in theyr rebellyon, pretende ſome tytle of reformation, myndinge in dede ruine and deſtruction: ſo doth his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels pretende that they be moued by the goſpell, which is the lawe of the Church, but as it is in vayne to alege the lawe ageynſt rebels: ſo it is in vayne to aleage the ſcripture and to dyſpute with heretyckes, but as the power of the realme muſt be bent ageynſte rebelles, ſo muſt the multitude of the learned men, that haue byn and yet be defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders ageinſt the aſſaultes of heretickes. The thyrde thynge that the houſe of god is knowen by, from the houſe of the deuyll, is the conſente, the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vnitie of fayth that is in Gods houſe. For as the Prophet ſayth,<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> In the houſe of Godde they walked
<pb facs="tcp:5395:30"/>with a conſente or agrement: and in anther place he ſayth, Beholde howe pleaſaunte a thynge it is for bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threne to dwell together,<note place="margin">Act. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and in the Actes of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles we rede, that they that were admitted fyrſt to this houſe, were couſentynge altogether in the temple. And ſaynt Paule wyllynge the Epheſyans to reteyne and kepe the ſame vnitie of fayth,<note place="margin">Ephe. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> ſayth to the Epheſynns, that as there is one Lorde, and one baptiſme: ſo muſte they haue one fayth. Alſo the ſame ſaint Paule biddeth the Romans to beware of ſuch as do ſowe diſcorde and contencion amongſt them.<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> Alſo for this vnitie to be the better meynteyned in his houſe, which is the Churche,<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>12. 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> lyke as God hath placed the members of the body in a moſt decent and neceſſary order, and hath apointed one member to be the chiefeſte, or as it is called the head: ſo hath God apointed in his Church diuers degrees of myniſters, and one heade of them all, who for the time of the Apoſtles was ſaynt Peter, and afterwardes as it doth well apere by the hyſtoryes from tyme to tyme, were his ſucceſſours the byſhops and popes of Rome: But contrarywyſe in the houſe of the deuyll there be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities of religions, ſectes, continuall mutacion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencion, and to be briefe: in dede nothynge, but a babi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonicall confuſion. To be ſhorte, nowe the Church, as I haue ſayde, is knowen by theſe markes, fyrſt by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, ſecondely by the largeneſſe, or vniuerſalneſſe, and thyrdely by conſent and vnitie. But here perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture ſome wyll ſaye that yf I ſhulde meaſure the Churche by vniuerſalnes, or largenes, then ſhall the Turkes religion be the Churche, for that is moſt vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall.
<pb facs="tcp:5395:31"/>And yf I ſay that the Churche ſhalbe deſerned by the conſente of the doctoures, then it is certeyne that the doctours do not in all thynges agree. To the fyrſte I aunſwere, that when I ſay that the church of Chriſt may be knowen by the vniuerſalnes of her place in the worlde, I do not ſay ſo to make thereby any difference betwyxte the Turkes religion and Chryſte, for that were altogether in vayne, ſeinge that the Turkes do not chalenge any parte or tytle of Chryſte to them, that men ſhulde nede to make notes to deſerne the Turkes and Chryſtes religion in ſunder: but I do ſaye it that men myght be able to deſerne betwyxte the herytycall Church, which chalengeth to it the tytle of Chryſt, and is not of hym. And the Catholyke Churche which hath the tytle, and is in dede Chryſtes. And touchynge the diſagreinge or error of the doctours. Fyrſte I ſaye that theyr diſagreinge is not ſuch as maketh partes, ſectes, faſhyons, and diuiſions from the whole bodye, heade, and members, nor yet for any neceſſary artycle of oure fayth, all which may be ſene to be amongſte the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes. For where the catholyke powers ſometymes diſcentynge amongſt them ſelues in matter of no great portion, do charitably without condempnynge eyther of other, or makynge of partes, eche ſufferynge the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to haue his or theyr opynyon: the heretyckes doo playne the contrary, deuidynge them ſelues from the heade and members, &amp; drawyng other to theyr partes, eche of them condempnynge other. Secondely I ſaye that though the doctours of the Church haue byn decea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued, or erred, yet do I ſay that they were neuer ſo vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſally
<pb facs="tcp:5395:31"/>deceaued: neyther was theyr error ſo vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally receaued, but that one or other haue eſpyed it and corrected it: and finally they haue eche others error ſo corrected, that looke whatſoeuer is vniuerſall and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke, that is moſt ſuer to be free from error, ſo that though the doctours may be deceaued euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his priuate iudgement, yet that whereupon they all do agree muſt nedes be moſt true, for without the eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial grace of the holy ghoſt (who is always there where men be gethered together in Chryſtes name) it were vnpoſſible that ſo many men of learnynge, and of ſuch zeale towardes the trueth, ſhulde otherwyſe agree then of a truthe in deede. Thus then good people haue I taught this fayth that is ſo neceſſary, that without it all that we haue is nothynge, what it is, and who is the ſchole maſter and teacher of it, what the thinges be that we muſt learne by it, and who be fitte ſchollers for it. Alſo I haue tolde you howe you muſte vſe it, that is, ye muſt in ſuch ſorte beleue in God the teacher of it, that ye muſt be as chyldren that knoweth nothyng but him, and that taketh and learne the all thynges to be as he doth teache you, &amp; that doth not prouyde for your ſelfe, but aſke and craue the thynges that ye wante of hym, and that ye muſt obey him as moſte louynge chyldren. Thyrdly, I haue ſhewed you howe nedefull it is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, &amp; to take hede of the ghoſtly enemy the deuyl that he deceaue not the ſimplicitie of your fayth, and how ye may knowe to auoyde the danger, the which thing that we may all do, god out heauenly father graunt, &amp; giue vs grace, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be honour and praiſe worlde without ende. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:32"/>
            <head>Of the primatiue and chiefe auctoritie.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ilitia eſt vita hominis ſuper terram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> Mans lyfe (ſayth Iob) is a warfare vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon the earth. A wonders thynge good people, to ſe what miſery we be in whiles we be here, as it appereth by the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye of this holye father, for we be not borne (ſayth he) to playe and paſtyme, but we be borne to be warryers: And ageynſte whome do we feyght trowe ye? Verely ſayth ſaynt Paule our feyght is not ageynſte u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eſhe and blood,<note place="margin">Ephe. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> but ageynſte the foule and myghty fiendes of hell, neyther do we ſtryue to be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered out of temporall bondage, whiche ſhall haue an ende, but out of the bondage that is endeleſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall. O howe terrible is that place,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.</note> where there is no comfort to be founde? O howe greuous are thoſe tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, where not one ioynt of our bodies or ſowles ſhal be free?<note place="margin">Totn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus prou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatur in gehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nam. Math. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Do ye knowe what peyne it is to haue but one ſore fynger? What is it then to haue al the body &amp; ſowle enwrapped in the endeleſſe ſorowe and wo. If we win the fielde, our toy and tryumph ſhalbe ſuch as no harte can thinke, nor tounge (as the prophet ſaith) can ſpeke: Seinge then that we beinge as babes muſte fyght a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſt ſuch a great gyaunt as the deuyll is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſie.</hi> 64. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> and for ſo great a pryce as heauen and hell be. Se I praye you howe manfull we ought to be, and what preparaunce and redineſſe is neceſſary for this fielde, and how much we ought to procure out owne ſaftie. Do ye not ſe what preparaunce men vſe to make,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> when they wyll feyght
<pb facs="tcp:5395:32"/>ageynſt theyr temporall enemies? And ſhall not we do it much more in this battel with our ghoſtly enemies? Is there not greater danger in this, then in that. And what is the chiefeſte defence that the ſouldyers haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geynſt theyr enemies? Is it not the kepynge of theyr aray? is not then the battell loſt, when the aray is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? And doth not ſaynte Paule call vppon vs to kepe our aray, when he ſayth,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.</note> let euery man abyde in that vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cation that he is called in, whether he be Iewe or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll: But howe then can we kepe our araye yf we haue no capytayne? Do ye not ſe that it is neceſſary in an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that he whiche is the chiefeteyne do appoynte ſome liefetenaunt by whoſe authoritie the ſouldiers maye be ſet in theyr aray, and that by hym ſuch may be puniſhed as wyll nedes breke theyr aray. Euen ſo good people,<note place="margin">Roma. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> it is neceſſary in the Church of God to haue heades and rulers, to kepe vs in an order whyles we feyght ageinſt the deuyll,<note place="margin">Nemo ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi preſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Hebre. <hi>5.</hi> Quod ſig nis non o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedit. <hi>2.</hi> Theſſ. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> that when ſo euer the deuyll ſhall labour ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by vicious behauour to brynge vs in a damnable condicion of lyuynge, or by wronge vnderſtandyng of the ſcriptures into hereſy and miſbeliefe, men maye be kept in theyr aray, &amp; not euery man ſuffered to do &amp; ſay what hym <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſteth, the lacke of the which gouernaunce, what it hath done in this realme, and what confuſyon we haue bin brought vnto, al the whole realme to their great griefe doth feele.<note place="margin">Prouer. <hi>11</hi>
               </note> We ſe nowe howe true it is that Salomon ſayth, <hi>Vbi non eſt gubernator corruit ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas,</hi> that is to ſay, where there is no gouernour the cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie decayeth, ſeinge therfore both the ſwarmes of vyce and of opinions, that hath ouerwhelmed this region,
<pb facs="tcp:5395:33"/>which was before ſuch confuſion) one of the welthyeſte regions in Chryſtendome.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> And ſeinge that we knowe by the report of the ſcriptures, that we be ſpiritual ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyers, and therfore muſt haue a ſpirituall head, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge we knowe nowe by experience (at the leſt ſuche as haue regarde to god and to heauen) the euyls that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue vpon our aray or order beinge broken, and fynally we herynge Chryſt our kynge ſaynge to our capitaines that who ſo receaueth them receaueth hym,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> and who ſo diſpyſeth them diſpyſeth hym: we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to thinke that it muſt be much for our commoditie and ſafety al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. Fyrſt to knowe whether there be any ſuch capitayne apoynted of god or not. Secondely, when and howe they were apoynted. And thyrdely, that we may the bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter obey them, and be ruled by them, It is neceſſary to knowe who they be. The which thynges done, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently perſwaded by gods worde, I doubt not but al true Chryſten men and women wyl be ruled and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them. Wherefore in this homyly or ſermonde (good people) ſhalbe intreated theſe thre thynges. Firſt whether god doth apoynte any ſuche authoritie or not. Secondely when and howe he apoynteth them. And thyrdely who they be that are ſo apoynted. At our firſt enterynge or goinge towardes this great and weyghty matter, I ſhall deſyre you and charge you alſo in gods behalfe, that ye put from you the vayne opinion, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the errour of fortune, that is, that ye thynke not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thynge to be done by fortune, as who ſhuld ſay, he is ryche, he is poore, he is a man of honoure, he is a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunte, he is hanged, or drowned, bycauſe it was his
<pb facs="tcp:5395:33"/>warde or fortune. For there is no ſuch fortune or ward in dede, but all thynges are ruled and diſpoſed by god, in ſo much that Chryſt our ſauyour ſayth,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> that not one ſparrowe falleth into the fowlers net but by Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poyntment, much more then be the diuerſities of mans callynge of God.<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> Ageyne when the tower of Silo fell and ſlewe certeyne perſons, it myght haue bin thought of ſome that the tower fell by chaunce, and that it was thoſe mens deſteny there to be at the fall. But Chryſte ſaythe playnely that it was done purpoſely of God, to giue occaſion to other ſinners to beware, leſt god by one meane or other myght deſtroy them alſo, lyke as he did thoſe by the fal of the tower. Further where ſome do at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the lucke that men haue, to the ſtarres that men be borne vnder, god teacheth the contrary by the prophe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye of the holy woman Anna, and ſayth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Regſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dominus pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perum facit, et ditat, humiliat, et ſubleuat, de ſterco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re erigens paupetem vt ſolium gloriae teneat,</hi> that is, the Lord maketh poore, &amp; maketh rych, he humbleth &amp; exalteth, rayſyng the poore out of the myre, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might haue the ſeate of glory. Alſo in his prophet Ieremie he ſayth, <hi>Iuxta vias gentium nolite diſcere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>et a ſignis cae li nolite metuere, quae timent gentes, quia leges popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum vanae ſunt,</hi> that is. Lerne not ye to do after the faſhyons of the gentyles, neyther ſtande ye in awe to the ſignes of the firmament as the Gentyles do, for the lawes of the &amp; entyles be vayne. Thus may ye then ſe (good people) howe that all our plaſynge, be we ryche or poore, maſter or ſeruauntes, offycers or pryuate per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons be of God. For neyther is there ſparrowe caught
<pb facs="tcp:5395:34"/>nor the fyſhe gathered into the net, neyther the ſtones do fall, but by gods ordinaunce, yea and concernynge ſuch as be placed in authoritie, though they be euyl, yet be they of God.<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> For the holye Patryarche Job ſaythe, <hi>Propter peccata populi facit regnarey pocritam,</hi> that is, for the ſinnes of the people, he hath made the Ipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite to rule. And as ye knowe, there were neuer worſe rulers then were the Scrybes and the Phariſeis that put our ſauyour vnto death, and yet dyd Chryſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde that they ſhulde be obeyed, bicauſe they ſate in Moyſes ſete.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> But what other I pray you was it to ſitte in Moyſes ſeate, but that the ſame God that had fyrſte placed Moyſes for his tyme, placed the Pharyſes for theyr time, and therfore were they to be obeyed for their rowmes, though theyr perſons were very bad and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. And accordynge to the ſame ſayth ſaynte Paule, that all powers be of god, and that who ſo euer reſiſteth the power,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Roma.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Petri.</hi> 3.</note> reſiſteth god. Yea ſaynte Peter wylleth not onely vs to obey them, but that we ſhulde ſuffer them, though they beinge euyll, ſhulde do vs wronge. But nowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeinge that fortune nor chaunce hath no place in dede, but were fayned of ſuch as knowe not god, and ſeinge alſo that the ſcripture teachethe, that al pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be of god: it foloweth that we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider what powers they be, and wherein theyr auctoritie conſiſteth, for as it is neceſſary to knowe ſuch, bycauſe we muſt in peyne of gods diſpleaſure and wrath obey them, ſo muſte we knowe wherein theyr auctoritie lyeth, leſt that we obey them other wyſe then we ſhulde or ought, for ſome tyme we do ſe that obedience is praiſed as Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth
<pb facs="tcp:5395:34"/>it vnto vs, when he hym ſelfe payed tribute, and badde that we ſhulde gyue to Ceſar, that which was Ceſars,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>7.</hi> Math. <hi>22</hi> Actes. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and to God, that that was Goddes, and the Apoſtles were commended in the Actes for diſobeyinge the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, when they wolde haue had them to deny Chryſte. Thus it is neceſſary for al men to knowe where, howe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; when they ſhulde obey, or not obey. The which thing that ye may the better perceaue, cal I beſech you to your remembraunce the fyrſt creation of man: how that the ſcripture ſayth,<note place="margin">Gene. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that god faſhioned man vppon the earth, by the which is vnderſtande that mans body (the which man hath common to hym, with the beaſtes who be lykewyſe made of the earth, and feadeth vppon the earth and earthly thynges as man doth) yet (ſaythe the ſcripture) god did inſpyre into man the ſprite of life, by the which is ment that mans ſowle came frome god hym ſelfe, and is of ſubſtaunce and nature lyke vnto the Angels. Wherfore as theſe partes be of dyuers na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and condicions, and they both greatly nedeth to be well guyded and ordered, ſo hath almyghty god ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for that purpoſe both temporall and ſpirituall rulers: temporall rulers, by whoſe gouernaunce our bodyes and temporall goodes apperteyninge vnto vs, ought to be ordered, and we in all thoſe thynges obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent vnto them, yea though it do appere to our loſſe and hynderaunce accordynge to the ſayinge of ſaynt Peter who doth ſay, <hi>Obedite omni humanae creature propter deum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Petri.</hi> 2</note> 
               <hi>ſine regi quaſi precellenti ſine duci tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> abeo miſſo. &amp;c.</hi> That is ſayth ſaynt Peter. Obey you to all humayne creature, for gods ſake, whether it be a kinge
<pb facs="tcp:5395:35"/>as a perſon preexcellente, or els to a capitayne, as ſent from hym. And ſpirituall rulers by whoſe councelles and appointmentes we ought to be ordered in matters that do touch our ſowles health. And here vppon ſayth ſaynt Paule,<note place="margin">Hebre. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> obey ye your rulers, and be ordered by them, for they do watch as men that muſte gyue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for your ſowles. Here ye ſe that he named them ſpirituall rulers, bycauſe they be charged with oure ſowles, and commaundeth that we ſhulde be alſo obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient. For howe can they account for vs, yf we wyl not be ordered by them? And the ſame ſaynte Paule alſo ſheweth howe and in what ſort god doth appoint them, ſayinge,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. <hi>Roma.</hi> 12.</note> that as the body is one, and yet hathe dyuers me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers apoynted for dyuers vſes, ſo hath the myſtycal body of Chryſt, which is the Churche. Se here I pray you good Chryſten people, howe the bleſſed Apoitle of Chryſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth to vs the holy ſacrament of orders, he compareth the Churche to a body, in the creation of which body, who knoweth not, that at the fyrſt there is no diſtinction of members, as we ſe dayely in a negge that is to be hatched into a chycken. At the fyrſt there is no becke, there is no foote, there is no wynge, no eye, nor tounge, neyther is it poſſible for any, but for hym that maketh the chicken to ſay, that this part of the egge ſhalbe ſuch a member, and this ſuch, but god taketh one parte of the egge, maketh it an eye, and giueth it power onely to ſe, an other a foote, and giueth it habilitie to go and ſo forth, and no diuerſitie is there before that they be placed, and haue receaued of gods gyftes agreable vnto theyr places. Euen ſo good people, before the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb facs="tcp:5395:35"/>of orders receaued, they that be to be ordered and the reſidue be as one. But after the orders recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, lyke as they haue other places and romes the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they had before, ſo haue they other vertues and gyftes gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to them by the holy ghoſt, to worke and to do thoſe thynges that do apperteyne vnto theyr duties. For as Chryſt our ſauyoure ſaythe, it is not the mynyſter that ſpeaketh, but the ſprite of our father that ſpeaketh in the miniſter: In ſo much that Cayphas beinge a wycked man, yet bicauſe he was a byſhop,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>10.</hi> Iohn. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> the holy ghoſt ſpake in hym, and he prophecyed that Chryſt ſhulde dye for the people. And Balaam though he was an euyl man,<note place="margin">Nu. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> yet bycauſe he was a prophet appointed of God, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ghoſt dyd not let to ſpeke in hym. This thynge good people, is not eaſely ſene but of vs that be faythfull,<note place="margin">Niſi credi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deritis no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> intellige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis. Eſe. <hi>7 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> and doth knowe that almyghty God (who doth in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all thynges deuyde the partes of the ſede or mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter wherof he wolde make any thynge, in ſortinge and in diſpoſynge them into dyuers places, geueth dyuers gyftes, accordynge as the place requyreth, gyueth me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> placed in dyuers romes, vertues, and power, that be requiſite in ſuch romes, the which thynge, bycauſe it is ſene of vs that do beleue, and not of ſuche as be fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe or Infidels, therfore it is called a ſacramente and a myſtery. And therefore no marueyle good people, though our newe deuines and fleſhely goſpellers,<note place="margin">Petuerta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turas ad ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peruicie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>2.</hi> Petri. <hi>3</hi>
               </note> can not vnderſtande the myſtery of gods doyng in this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of orders, for as they vſe the ſcripture with no leſſe vnreuerent talke, geſtyng, yea with wreathyng of it accordyng vnto theyr fonde braynes and phanſies
<pb facs="tcp:5395:36"/>then they wolde or myght do a tale of Robyn hood, or ſuch lyke bookes of vanitie, ſo do they thynke no deale more to be done by god in this holy ſacrament, then yf they in playes ſet out by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do to the perſons who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they apoynt players. And for this cauſe amongſte them do euery man preache that lyſt, euery man miniſter that lyſteth. And yf they do admytte any, they ſaye no more to hym but go, be a preacher, or a miniſter, or ſuch lyke, as who ſhulde ſay all theſe were offyces of pollicie, and not materiall to religion. But to let this paſſe: ye muſt knowe that this worde order ſygnyfieth dyſtyncte pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynges, and degrees of men in theyr roomes, of the which ſome be hygher and ſome be lower, and ſome the hygheſt of al other. And ſe I pray you howe this worke of god agreeth with al his other workes. Fyrſt is it not certeyne that in heauen there be many orders of Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and eche of them hygher then other, and onely al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myghty god the hygheſte and aboue all other? Do ye not ſe in the firmamente dyuers bryghtnes to be in the ſtarres,<note place="margin">Collo. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and yet the ſonne to be the bryghteſt of them al? Are there not degrees amongſt the fowles:<note place="margin">Collo. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and yet the Eegle kynge of them all. Do not the beaſtes one excell another, and are not they all vnder the Lyon? What ſhulde I ſpeke of the Cranes when they flye, haue they net theyr Capitayne and guyde: Is there not alnongſt the bees one maſter bee, vnto whome all the reſidue be obedient? In the bodyes both of man and beaſtes, is there not one principal part commonly called the head? And where haue ye ſene any common wealth well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned where there hath not byn one heade? Euen ſo
<pb facs="tcp:5395:36"/>good Chriſten men and wouren hath god done and ſtyl dothe appoynte one to be heade and gouernoure in his Church. As fyrſt to begyn at Aron,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> dyd not God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynt hym alone for his tyme to be the heade and chiefe of all the Leuytes and prieſtes? when he was departed was not Eleazer appoynted the chiefe byſhop ouer the reſt?<note place="margin">Nume. <hi>20</hi>
               </note> what ſhulde I nede to ſpeake muche of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Is it not euident euen vnto the commynge of oure ſauyour Chryſt, that the principalitie or hygh degree of prieſt hodde dyd ſtyll continue, and that there was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways one aboue the al reſidue? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chryſt came, dyd not he make lyke diuerſitie of his diſciples?<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>10.</hi> Luke. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> Dyd not he chooſe out of the whole number that folowed hym. <hi>72.</hi> that were called diſciples? and did he not vſe his twelue Apoſtles more familierly then them.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>17</hi>
               </note> And dyd he not choſe forth from amongſte the Apoſtles, Peter, Iohn and Iames, to be more nere to him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other were, for they onely were ſuffered to ſe his glorious tranſfigu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration?<note place="margin">Math. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> And may we not ſe that aboue them and all the reſidue Chryſt to haue appoynted ſaynt Peter?<note place="margin">Marke. <hi>3.</hi> Luke <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Fyrſte conſider howe all the Euangeliſtes when they number the Apoſtles. they begin alway with Peter, in ſo much that ſaynt Luke beinge a diſciple to ſaynte Paule, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not ſo to do, &amp; for what other cauſe ſhulde all they and in euery place begyn with Peter, but bycauſe that they toke hym to be the chiefeſt of the Apoſtles.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>20</hi>
               </note> But ye wyll ſay that Chriſt rebuked the Apoſties for that they ſtroue which of them ſhulde be the greateſt: Truth it is he blamed them in that they deſyred ſuperioritie. But he denyed not to gyue it to ſuch as deſired it not, for he
<pb facs="tcp:5395:37"/>ſayth, he that wyll be the greateſt amongſt you, muſt be ſeruaunt to the reſidue, by the which he ſheweth both a ſuperitorytie to be, &amp; alſo teacheth what maner of one it ſhulde be, ſayinge, that it ſhulde be a common ſeruice to all the other.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> Ageyne when that Chriſt gaue authoritie to loſe and to bynde to all the Apoſtles, yet in that he na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth Peter, and not the reſidue, it is playne, that as he gaue the offyce to all, ſo dyd he in the offyce preferre Peter to them all. Further when our ſauyoure before his death taught to them the greate daunger that they ſhulde be in at his death, ſayinge, that the deuyll deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſyft them, euen as wheate is ſyfted in the ryddle, yet he ſayde to Peter, that he hadde deſyred god his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that Peters fayth ſhulde not quayle,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> and therfore bad hym that when he was conuerted, that he ſhulde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme and ſtay the reſidue, whereby doth appere that Chryſt dyd preferre Peter fyrſt, in that he had a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall promeſſe that he ſhulde not ſhrynke, and faynt for feare, and then that he commyted all the reſidue to be confirmed by hym. Ageyne when Chryſte was ryſen from death, dyd he not commyte the whole charge of his Churche more preſently to Peter then to the other? Why els ſhulde he ſay rather to Peter then to the other loueſt thou me,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> yea and that thryſe at euery aunſwere that Peter made affirminge that he loued Chryſte, he commaundynge that he ſhulde feede. Nowe yf that Chryſt dyd ſpecially charge Peter with feedynge, yea both the ſheepe, and alſo me thynketh that Chryſt made Peter his eſpeciall and chiefe ſhepherde. Moreouer in the Actes when Chryſte called forth Peter fyrſte to<note place="margin">Actes. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:5395:37"/>preache the goſpell to the gentyles, dyd it not apere that Peter was the chiefeſt of the Apoſtles, and that it was done bycauſe the Apoſtles and Diſciples ſhulde with the better wyll receaue the gentyles to the felowſhyppe of the goſpell, ſeinge hym to be made a preacher and a teacher to the gentyles that was chiefeſt amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ageyne when the apoſtles were altogether at the recea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge of the holy ghoſte, and when the councell of the Apoſtles was fyrſte gethered together at Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">Actes. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> dyd not Peter onely ſpeake, and ſhewe the cauſes of theyr ſpeakynge with dyuers tounges, and of the Abro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacion of the Iewes lawe amongſt the gentyles.<note place="margin">Actes. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> For though Iames dyd afterwardes ſpeake, yet he dyd it rather confirmyng that that was propounded by ſaint Peter, then chalengynge any authoritie to hym ſelfe. For he reherſed as a profe therof the tale y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſaynt Peter tolde, which was howe god hadde wrought by hym the conuerſion of the Gentyles.<note place="margin">Actes. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> Howe be it ſome wyll ſaye that Peter muſt nedes therfore be not the thefe, bicauſe that ſaynt Luke ſayth hym and Iohn to haue byn ſente into Samarie, that by them the Samaritans myght receaue the holy ghoſt. But nowe ſaye our newe men, in as much as they ſent Peter, and he that is ſent muſt be inferiour to hym that ſendeth hym, ſo muſt Peter be inferiour to the reſt of the Apoſtles, beinge ſent by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But here they myght ſe, yf they lyſte to marke, the vſe that is and alwayes hath bin in the Church concerning the ſacrament of confirmation, which is in dede the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of the holy ghoſte, that Peter muſte therefore be chiefe, bycauſe he was ſent to miniſter this ſcramente.
<pb facs="tcp:5395:38"/>For where haue ye ſene good people, any prieſte inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to a byſhoppe to miniſter confirmation vnto your thyldren? Then as confirmation belongethe to the thiefeſt of the prieſtes, ſo in as much as they ſente hym and Iohn to miniſter it, it is euidente that amonge all the reſidue they were the chiefe. And notwithſtanding that the reſidue of the Apoſtles were preſent, when the ſicke perſons were led into places to be ouerſhadowed with theyr ſhadowes, yet doth ſaynt luke make mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of none by name but of Peters ſhadow, the whiche ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth a preheminence to haue bin in Peter aboue al the reſt.<note place="margin">Auguſtine queſti. <hi>75.</hi> ſuper no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum. Chriſoſt. homile. <hi>55</hi> ſuper Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thewe. Iorome contra Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ninian li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber primo</note> And it apperteyneth playnely by ſaint Auguſtin in ſundry places of his woorkes, and ſpecially by his <hi>.75.</hi> queſtion that he wryteth vpon the newe teſtament. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Chryſoſtome in the <hi>.55</hi> homile vpon Mathewe, that one fyſher man was made capytayne and ruler of the ſhyppe that ſhulde be ſore toſſed, but neuer drowned, with the blaſtes of temptacion. Alſo ſaynte Ierome in his fyrſt booke ageynſt Ioninian ſayth. <hi>Supra Paetrum fundatur eccleſia, licet idipſum in alio loco ſuper om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Apoſto los fiat, et cuncti claues regni accipierunt et ex eaquo ſuper eos fortitudo ſolidatur, tamen prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea inter duodecim vnus eligatur, vt in capite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituto ſciſinatis tollatur occaſio.</hi> That is to ſay. The Churche is founded vppon Peter, althoughe the ſame thynge is ſayde to be done in another place, vpon al the Apoſtles and al they tooke the keyes of the kingdome, and ſtrength is faſtened indifferently vpon all, yet ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore one muſt be choſen amongſt the .xii. that in the head appoynted, the occaſion of diſcorde may be taken away.
<pb facs="tcp:5395:38"/>To be briefe, it is the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all the auncient fathers, that ſaynt Peter was the chiefe of the Apoſtles. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as there was before Chryſtes tyme, &amp; in Chriſtes tyme, and alſo after hym a chiefe and one aboue al the reſidue, ſo hath it continued vnto this miſerable tyme and bycauſe that it is not nowe, ſo therfore are theſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries fallen vppon vs that be. wherefore ſeinge we ought to haue a heade, and ſtande as muche neede of a heade as euer dyd they, all good men muſt thynke it of neceſſitie, that a heade we muſt haue. Vnto this then it is requyred to knowe where this head ſhuld be, &amp; who he is, that we may knowe hym, and ſo conſequently o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey as it is holſome for vs to do. without all doubte (good Chryſten people) his place is the ſee of Rome, &amp; the byſhop of that ſea hath always bin, &amp; ought nowe by Gods word to be the head of al byſhops. For as he that ſuccedeth the kynge by ryght, ought of ryght to be kynge. So he that doth ryghtuouſly ſuccede ſaynt Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter beinge the chiefe of all the Apoſtles, ought of ryght to be the chiefe of byſhoppes. Ageyne god hath not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted eyther to Peter, or to any other lyke authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie as Peter had, not for his owne commoditie or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte, but for the edifyenge of the Church: wherfore ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the Churche remayned after Peter, ſo muſte the ſame authoritie that Peter hadde ſtyll remayne in the Church, and it muſt alſo be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be in the Church. But ſuch authoritie may only be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to remayne in the biſhop of Rome being ſucceſſor to ſaint Peter, or els it muſt be vncerteyne yf any other ſhulde haue it, and ſo conſequently vnprofytable. wherefore it muſt nedes
<pb facs="tcp:5395:39"/>be that it remayneth in him. Ageyne we ſay that ageinſt the commynge of our ſauyour Chryſte, God had made Rome the heade of the worlde in all temporalties,<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly as it is to be thought, bycauſe that by Chriſt it ſhulde be made a heade of ſpiritualties. In the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Iury thoughe there were manye cities, yet was there one eſpecially choſen to God, and that was Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, to be theyr chiefe citie. And nowe when the Churche was to be ſpredde through the worlde, he hath choſen Rome as it is to be thought to be aboue the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due, which appeareth by two cauſes. The fyrſt is, that of al the great ſees that be in the world, it hath alwayes byn moſte free and pure from hereſie. God alwayes haue defended the ſame, where all the reſidue, as Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Antyoche, Epheſus, and the other Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke Churches are deſtroyed, and this onely doth ſtyll remayne, and is by God defended. The thyrde cauſe may be added that all good Chryſten men haue euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more taken it to be the heade, as it maye apere by the decree of Conſtantine, that moſte godly and Chriſtian Emperour,<note place="margin">Prefa. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine Nice.</note> which is ſette before the councell of Nyce, wherein he confeſſeth the ſee of Rome to be the chiefeſt ſee, and Silueſter to be the chiefeſt byſhop. It apereth alſo to haue byn obſerued afterwardes. In ſo muche that in the tyme of Conſtantius the Emperour it was layed to the charge of the Arryans (who had made to them ſelues a councell at Antioche) that they had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the olde cannons and decrees of the Church,<note place="margin">Tripti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hiſt. lib. <hi>4</hi> Capi. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> which dyd forbydde that any councell ſhulde be gathered, but by the aduyce of the byſhop of Rome. Theſe decrees
<pb facs="tcp:5395:39"/>they ſayde were then olde which gyue this authoritie to the ſee of Rome, and it is ſence this buſines was nere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. <hi>1200.</hi> yeres, muſt it not then be auncient now trowe ye? Saynte Auguſtine alſo in his. <hi>162.</hi> epyſtle bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myng the diſſimulation of one Secundus that had bin vnconſtaunt in a matter that was before hym, and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tedyng that he did it to meinteine peace, ſaith that there was no cauſe for hym to feare the breache of peace in that matter hauynge the conſent of the ſee of Rome on his parte, in the which Church the chiefe of the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke ſee dyd floryſhe. Saynt Ierome alſo beſydes that he ſayth <hi>ad Damaſum,</hi> that he wyll alwayes folowe that fayth that is taught in the ſee of Rome, and rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge the Luciferaunce for theyr ſcyſme doth ſaye alſo that there muſt be a certeyne principalitie or chiefety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt prieſtes or els there ſhalbe as many ſciſmes as there be prieſtes. To theſe may we adde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> article of our fayth, which is that we beleue the holy Catholike &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolyke Church, the meaninge of the which article is. Firſt in that we ſay that we beleue the catholike church, we ſay that we do beleue the Church that is vniuerſall and generally ſpredde through the worlde, wherby we refuſe all hereſy and pryuate doctrine, and in that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that we do name it Apoſtolyke, we do profeſſe our ſelues to be confirmable to that ſee that the Apoſtle dyd rule and bere offyce in. But nowe is there none that hathe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles byſſhoppes ſauynge Rome, and when there were lyke as Peter was the chiefeſt of the Apoſtles, ſo was that ſee aboue all the other ſees, and therfore eyther we muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fes it to be chiefe, or els deny our beliefe. Thus
<pb facs="tcp:5395:40"/>then may ye ſe good people, howe neceſſary it is to haue a heade, by whom we may be ſet in aray to fight ageinſt the deuyll. Ye ſe alſo that all powers and romes be of Godde, and not of fortune, ye ſe that as we haue twoo partes, our bodyes and our ſowles, ſo God hath apoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to vs two gouernoures, the one temporall, and the other ſpiritual: ye ſe that as God doth giue dyuers ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tues and powers to euery member that he placeth in the felowſhyppe of our bodyes, ſo doth he to thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he promoteth by the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of orders, ye knowe why it is called a ſacrament, ye ſe what order God doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue in all his workes, and that they haue theyr ende in one chiefe or ruler, ye ſe that it was apoynted before Chryſt to haue one heade, it was ſo ordeyned by Chriſt and ſo ye ſe that it ought to continue. And in this we knowynge oure capitaynes, or romes, let vs all kepe our aray, and ſtandynge, and be obedient vnto our prynces appoynted to vs by God, and when the greate and ioyfull tryumphe ſhalbe in heauen vppon the deuyll, and all his members, then ſhall we be rewarded for oure faythfulnes of God the father, of Chryſt our chiefe Capitaine, &amp; of the holy ghoſt, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be honour and prayſe nowe and euer. Amen</p>
         </div>
         <div type="homily">
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:40"/>
            <head>Of confeſſion and purgation or clenſynge from ſinne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Aſſhe your ſelues, and be ye cleane, take away the euilnes of your thoughtes forth of my ſight,<note place="margin">Eſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſayth almyghty god in his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet Eſay, by the whiche wordes (good people) we be taught, that as ſuche muſt be very comely and honeſt in theyr apparell, that ſhalbe much conuerſaunt in the houſes of noble men and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo ought we Chriſten men to be moſte cleane and pure in our ſowles, that be dayely conuerſaunte, not in the houſe, but openly in the ſyght of hym that is the prynce of all prynces, and lorde of all Lordes, neyther is he alone when he ſeeth vs, but is accompanyed and wayted vpon with infinite numbers of bleſſed ſprytes, both of Angels and of men, yea he dothe ſo ſe vs, that we be neyther nyght nor day in the Church, or at home, yea in the fyelde, or in the maket,<note place="margin">Quorum angeli vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentur. Math. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> out of his ſyght. More ouer he commeth ſo to vs, that he dwelleth in vs, Is it not then neceſſary for vs, to waſſhe oure ſelues and to make our ſelues honeſt, that be thus continually way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge vpon god, and that hath alſo his bleſſed angels waytynge vppon vs? Is there any of the kynges ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes that wyll apeare before hym in a ragged lyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, or in a fowle ſpotted and greacy cote? wyl they not hyde theyr ſores and botches of theyr bodyes alſo, yf they haue any that be euyll fauoured, and that can not be healed: and with what diligence then ſhulde we pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pare our ſelues to apere before our maſter? But ye wyl ſay this is the delicateneſſe and nyſenes of men, in god
<pb facs="tcp:5395:41"/>there is no ſuch nyſe curteſy, nor curious niſeneſſe? yes verely. For why doth he els waſhe vs, when he recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs fyrſte into his grace and famuly, but that he wolde haue vs to continue clenly.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> And why ſaythe he, <hi>Beati mundo corde quoniam ipſi deum videbunt.</hi> Bleſſed be the cleane in harte for they ſhall ſe God, but that they whoſe hartes be fowle, ſhall not be ſuffered to come to goddes ſyght? And howe greuous thynkeye, wolde it be to one that had bin of the priuie chamber, to be ſhutte out of the kynges ſyght? And howe wolde it greue the chylde to be put forthe of his fathers pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence? Therfore (good people) as he that is clenly wyl neure be without water, neyther wyll the courtyers want thoſe ornamentes that maye commende them in the kynges ſyght, ſo ſhulde we that be Chryſten men haue our hole ſtudi &amp; labour to make our ſelues pleſant to Gods ſyght. But howe then may we that be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinfull,<note place="margin">Iacobi. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> decke our ſelues to apere honeſt in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of god. Truly ſaynt Iames ſayth, <hi>Emundate ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nus peccatores, et purificate corda duplices animo,</hi> that is. Make cleane your handes, O you ſinners, and purge your myndes ye that be double harted. So that by his councell, yf we do awaye the faultes whiche we haue wrought, and make cleane our hartes from fylth and vnlawfull thoughtes, then ſhall we be comely and honeſt. Nowe then to the intent that ye maye the better make your ſelues to apere honeſt and cleane in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and ſyght of God, three thynges are neceſſary to be conſidered, of the which the fyrſt is, to conſider what euyll and miſchiefe there is in ſinne, from the which we
<pb facs="tcp:5395:41"/>muſt purge and dyght vs, the ſeconde is,<note place="margin">Perditio tua ex te Iſrael ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modo in me auri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lium tun<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Oſe, <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> to know who muſt purge &amp; dyght vs, for we that can fyle our ſelues when we lyſt, can not make our ſelues cleane without helpe. The thyrde is howe we muſte vſe and behaue our ſelues towardes hym when he is aboute to purge and dyght vs. Fyrſt then for the euylneſſe of ſinne, it is to be knowen that ſinne doth ſo offende god, and make hym angry is ſuche ſorte with vs, that he wyll neyther heare vs, nor helpe vs, when we crye vnto ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hym, in ſo much that the prophet Dauyd ſayth of hym inge ſo deare to Godde as ye knowe that he was.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>65.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iniquitatem ſi afpexi in corde meo, non exaudiet deus</hi> It I ſe) ſayth Dauyd) an iniquitie in my hart, then I knowe that god wyll not here: yea the Iewes knewe and confeſſed alſo that god wolde not heare the prayer of a ſinner.<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> But what Chryſten hart thynketh it not to be an euyll aboue all euyles, a plage aboue all plages, and aboue all thynges to be feared, that maketh God, whom we in our prayers do call father, to ſhut vp his eares ageynſt our prayers? Is there any chyld, though he be but of one day olde,<note place="margin">Inte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectus ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex vtero. Pſal. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note> that ſtandethe more neede of his mother, then we do of God? Howe be it, yf the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dye when her chylde is but one nyght olde, yet her frendes may peraduenture noryſhe and brynge vp the chylde. But yf we be deuyded from god by our ſinnes, then we leeſe not hym alone, but we leeſe the loue and frendſhyp of al his bleſſed ſayntes our frendes, yea our brethrene, yf we were his chyldren. For they ſaye all with the prophet Dauyd. <hi>Nonne qui oderunt te domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne, oderam, et ſuper inimicos tuos tabeſcebam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>138.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto
<pb facs="tcp:5395:42"/>odio oderam illos, et inimici facti ſunt mihi.</hi> That is, O Lorde haue I not hated thoſe that thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt? haue not I waxed wanne with anger towardes thyne enemies? With a deadly hate haue I hated them, and they are alſo made myne enemies. And not onely god and his ſayntes are then ageinſt vs, but al the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that euer god made, doth that they can to puniſhe and to deſtroy vs, for howe coulde they otherwyſe do ſeruyce to theyr maſter, yf they ſhulde nat deſtroy, or at leaſt accordynge to theyr power vexe and punyſhe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. And therof it came that the redde ſea gaue place to the Iſraelites to paſſe, that were gods frendes, and dyd deſtroy the Egipnans that were his enemies,<note place="margin">Exod. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> the fyre which is a comfortable elemente to all men, dyd it not contrary to his owne nature (which is alway to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende and to go vpwarde and to burne) came downe and burned the Sodomites. And yet when Nabucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donoſar caſt the chyldren into it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 19. <hi>Daniel.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 13.</note> it dyd not once ſyndge or burne the heare of theyr heads. Did not a Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſle the Prophet of God that was ſent vnto the Iſraelites, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he contrary to gods commaundemente dyd eate and drynke there?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17</note> Did not beares deſtroy the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren that mocked Elizeus?<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 17</note> And yet Dauyd beinge a chylde ſlewe both a beare and a Lyon. But what ſhuld I ſtande longe in this matter, are not rauens &amp; kytes fowles that do punyſhe vs, and that do take our ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce away from vs, and yet dyd not they fede Heli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in the wylderneſſe? To be ſhorte, the plages that come by the tempeſtuouſnes of the ayer, by the vnfrute fulneſſe of the grounde, by myſe, rattes and other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,
<pb facs="tcp:5395:42"/>are not all theſe tokens of gods wrath towarder man? And therefore of it may apere to come that God hath ſo plaged vs Englyſhe men of late,<note place="margin">Dum diin dicamur a domino corripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus vt no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cum hoc mundo da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nemur. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>11. 1.</hi> Ioh. <hi>3.</hi> Iohn <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> bycauſe we haue offended hym in leauynge of oure catholyke and true fayth, and in ſteede therof haue eubraſed preſump<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuous reaſonynge vpon his holy myſteries and fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hereſy. Furthermore ſinne maketh vs ſeruauntes to the deuyll, for as ſaynte Iohn ſayth. <hi>Qui peccat ex diabolo eſt.</hi> He that ſinneth is of the deuyll. Doth not our ſauyour ſaye alſo, that he that committeth ſinne, is the ſeruaunt of ſinne? And what bondage is to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to that bondage whereby a man is made thral to the deuyll? Is the greate Turke to be compared to the deuyl? Or were it not better to be bounde to the Turke then to the deuyll? And why do we ſo much feare to be in bondage to the Turke or to any other tyranne,<note place="margin">Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perfi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentur ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcire, cete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> factis negant cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuit abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minabiles et dicro no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> audien<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes et ad omne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus bona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reprobi. Tit. <hi>1.</hi> Sapieu. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and ſo lyttle to the deuyl. Truly very infide litie is the cauſe therof. For yf we were as wel perſwaded in the deuyls, as we be in the Turkes, we wolde feare hym a greate deale more. But we haue preached of fayth, or rather prated of it ſo much that a number of vs are become ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry Infidels. For thoughe we profeſſe God with oure mouthes, yet with our deedes we deny hym. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more ſinne ſlayeth the ſowle of man. For as the wyſe man ſayth. <hi>Os quod mentitur occidit animam.</hi> The mouth that lyeth ſlayeth the ſowle. But alas, yf the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge mouth be a murderer of the ſowle, what murder and ſlaughter of ſowles ſhall we thynke to be nowe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, that vſe nothynge els almoſt but lying and diſceite? And this is alſo brought in, or at the leaſt much
<pb facs="tcp:5395:43"/>increaſeth by our newe fonde goſpell and fleſhely rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Nowe you ſe that yf a mans horſe or other beaſte be in daunger to peryſhe, there wyll be ſterrynge and runnynge to helpe. But yf a man chaunce to be in the peryll of drownynge, hangynge, or murderinge, there wolde be labour made of al handes to ſaue his lyfe, and well to. And yet we that be ſo buſye in preſeruynge of goodes, and in meinteynynge of the bodely lyfe, which wyll once haue an ende whether we wyll or not, be eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry daye occupyed in murderynge of ſowles, and that that is worſte of all other, we be murderers of oure owne ſowles, and ſuffer our chyldren and ſeruauntes, yea we teache them to do the ſame. But ſe here (good people) what is to be thought vpon other vyces? For if lyinge be ſuch an heynous and peryllous thynge, what then is murder? what is oppreſſion? what is thefte? what is whoredome, and all other kyndes of vyces? what woundes thynke you that they make in mans ſowle? Wherfore the euylland miſchiefe the which is in ſinne thus conſydered, it foloweth nowe that we muſte learne vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we may ſeke for remedy, that is, who muſt clenſe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it, &amp; that ſayth almyghty god in his prophet Eſay,<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> is God hym ſelfe, <hi>Ego ſum, ego ſum ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe qui deleo iniquitates tuas.</hi> It is I, it is I my ſelfe (ſayth god) that putteth away thy ſinnes.<note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>50.</hi>
               </note> And Dauyd alſo the moſt holy prophet deſyreth none other but god to waſhe hym from his ſinnes.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 2.</note> And ſaynte Iohn in his Epiſtle ſayth that Chryſte is onely the propiciation for our ſinnes.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> And the Iewes could ſay alſo, that no man coulde forgyue ſinnes, ſaue god alone, and ye ſe howe
<pb facs="tcp:5395:43"/>redy he is to do away our ſinnes in ſo much that he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs vnto hym for that purpoſe ſayinge.<note place="margin">Math. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Accedite ad me omnes qui laboratis, et one rati eſtis: et ego relie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am vos.</hi> Come vnto me all ye that labour, and be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy laden, and I ſhall refreſhe you.<note place="margin">Time. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> And ſaynte Paule ſayth, that Chryſt came into the worlde to ſaue ſinners. Is not here then a wonderfull clemencye of God that wyll not ceaſe (though we be ſo vnkynde to hym) to do away our ſinnes by hym ſelfe, yea that he doth offer him ſelfe vnto vs? Is not this a wonderous phiſition that is both ſo able and ſo wyllynge? Shall not we worthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly peryſhe that wyll not ſeeke remedye nowe when we haue it ſo frely offered vnto vs? Then ye wyl aunſwere that ye wolde go vnto god to be ryd from your ſinnes, but ye knowe not nowe where to fynde hym, eſpecially ſeinge nowe that the Turkes, the Iewes, the Artians, the Lutherans, the Oecholampadians, the Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſtes, the Libertines, and al other ſectes ſayth that god is onely with them. Howe be it, yf ye wyl knowe where god is: Verely he is onely in his kyngedome. And yf ye be deſyrous to knowe where the kyngedome of god is, he ſayth him ſelfe that it is amongſte you.<note place="margin">Luke. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> And leaſt peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ye might be deceaued by ſuche as do falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chalenge to them ſelues the kyngedome of God, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge here or there is Chryſt, he and his kyngedome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge nothynge leſſe then amongſte the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> he ſhewed then to you who they be that hath the kingedome of god re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynynge amongſt them, when he tooke the chyldren vnto hym and ſayde,<note place="margin">Math. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> of ſuch in dede is the kyngedome of God. Wherof it is to be ſene, that god doth onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne
<pb facs="tcp:5395:44"/>mayne amongſt the Catholykes, that is, amongſt ſuch as haue theyr fayth generall, for they be all ſo humble and meke, that they are al afrayde to reaſon vpon gods myſteries. For they knowynge theyr vnableneſſe to ſearche gods myſteries, had rather al to be ſcholers and learners, then maſters. And therefore bycauſe that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them euery one myſtruſteth hym ſelfe, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth more credyte to an other then to hym ſelfe; ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it to paſſe that they do agree amongſt them ſelues no man being ſo bolde as to teach any thynge the which he hath not lerned of another, ſo that theſe be the meke as children amongſt whom remayneth the kingedome of god,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> and vnto whom alſo the holy ghoſt is promiſed to be theyr ſchole maſter.<note place="margin">Si quis ſi bi videtur aliquid ſci re nondu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quicquam nouit que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: admodum oportet ſcire. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> Whereby it is to be ſene that the kyngedome of God can not be amongſt heretyckes, for the originall cauſe of hereſy is the truſte that man hath in his owne wytte, that is bycauſe he thynketh that he knoweth gods worde better, or that he hath a deeper ſyght in gods myſteries then other men haue, therfore thoſeth he to hym ſelfe a pryuate, and a newe vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge of gods worde, and doth eyther vtterly refuſe al authors, all generall councels, and the common beliefe of the whole worlde, or els ſyfteth them in ſuche ſorte, that where the heretyckes liſteth there they muſt ſerue,<note place="margin">Vbi enim emulatio et conteu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ibi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtantia et omne opus pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium. Iaco. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and where they lyſt not to recraue the authours or coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cels, there they muſt be refuſed. And this pryde is alſo the cauſe why they can not agree or longe continue in one beliefe, for amongſte them euery man lyke the his owne wyt beſt. Of this (good people) we haue had to much experience of late, the more is the pitie. Wherfore
<pb facs="tcp:5395:44"/>the kyngedome of heauen is not amongſt ſuche, and ſo conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly is not god to be ſought amongſt them, but in the Catholyke Churche, which is of meke and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearers, and not vppon ſtoute and preſumptuous preachers. Yea yf ye wyll come into this Church to ſeke Chryſt (for ye can not ſeke him there except ye come in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it) you muſt make your ſelues lowely and meke,<note place="margin">Nolite plures fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtri, ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes quod maius iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> for our ſauyoure ſaythe, that excepte you do humble your ſelues as Chyldren, ye ſhall not enter into the kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, ye muſte alſo leaue your deſyre to be teachers and reſoners, and ye muſte become meke and lowly ſcholers, ye may not take in hande to teache your fathers, but ye muſt be contente to be taught by them.<note place="margin">Iaco. <hi>3.</hi> Audi fili mi diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patris tui et ne dumittas legem ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tris tue vt addatur gratia ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piti tou, et torques collo tuo. Prouer. <hi>1.</hi> Actu. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> Seinge then that ye haue nowe learned where to fynd god who is the doer away of your faultes, it behoueth you to ſe hym, and to knowe hym when ye do ſe hym. For yf ye ſeke hym and do not knowe him, it is lyttle to purpoſe. But to knowe him in his perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſaynt Iohn it is playne that we can not, for he ſaythe, that no man hath ſene god at any tyme, what then thynke ye is beſte to be done? we muſt knowe God, and ye ſe that ſaynte Iohn ſayth that no man hath ſene God, howe then may we knowe him whom we neuer ſawe. Mary that ſaint Paule teacheth you in the Actes of the Apoſtles, for there he ſayth that God ſuffereth no man to be ignorant of hym. But howe doth he teache hym ſelfe to them, by ſyght trowe ye: No verely, but by the contemplacion of his workes, for he ſayth that God hath ſo made and appoynted the diuerſities of tymes, as of wynter, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and ſuch other lyke, and hathe ſo ordeyned mens
<pb facs="tcp:5395:45"/>habitacions and dwellynges, that if they wold but once grope for hym, they myght fynde hym. Marke here (good people) that he ſayth the workes of God to make hym ſo knowen to vs, that yf we wolde but once grope for hym we myght fynde him. And for the lyke purpoſe dyd our ſauyour Chryſt byd the Iewes that they ſhuld loke vnto his workes,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> for they dyd teache and bere wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of hym. And without doubt (good Chryſten peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) the knowledge that is gotten of Gods workes, is much more certeyne &amp; ſure then is the knowledge that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth by ſyght.<note place="margin">Opera ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cius annunciat firmamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum. Pſal. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> For lyke as a man ſhall better knowe a iudge when he ſeeth hym ſyt vpon the bench in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then goynge in the ſtrete amongſt other men, ſo are we taught to knowe God better by his workes, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if we ſhulde ſe hym as an Angel, or as a man amongſt other Angels or me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea but then we muſt marke, howe his workes doth teache hym, and what workes dothe teache hym, for certeyne it is that not his myracles or ſtrange workes doth teach hym onely, for then he ſhuld be taught but at certeyne tymes. And beſyde that to, the deuyl wyl worke miracles. But chiefely he is made knowen vnto vs by his ordinary workes, for thoſe can not the deuyll ſo ſone counterfeite, as he may myracles, and they be more generall alſo, and can the better by that meanes teache hym. And if ye wyll learne what theſe be, and howe they do teache, aſke of the huſbande man, and of the Princes, howe and of whome the one getteth his corne, the other the victory of his enemyes, and they wyll aunſwere that they both hath theſe, that is theyr corne, and theyr victory of god. And lykewyſe
<pb facs="tcp:5395:45"/>for the maner howe god doth gyue them,<note place="margin">Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> querite regunum. Math. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> the huſbande wyll ſay that god gyueth it by tyllage, the Prince wyll ſay that by the helpe of his army. And for theſe purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes do they fyrſt begyn theyr buſynes with prayer, that god wolde proſper them, and then they vſe gods ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary &amp; appoynted meane, bycauſe they wyll not tempt hym, and yet do they referre the ſucceſſe of theyr labour (yf they proſper) to hym, and not to them ſelues. Euen ſo deare brethrene hath god appoynted his ordynarye workes in his Churche, whereby we that be faythfull ought to knowe hym, as for example. He teacheth, but yet he doth it by the meane of the preacher, he waſſheth, but he dothe it by the ſacramente of babtiſme, he fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth you with his owne bleſſed body and blood, but he doth it by the moſt bleſſed ſacrament of the aulter, and ſo he doth purge and dyght you from your ſinnes, but lykewyſe he doth it by the ſacrament of penaunce, and marke I pray you, and ye ſhall not onely ſe hym in this ſacramente, but you ſhall here hym ſaye vnto you, thy ſinnes are forgeuen thee. O what a comfort is this to a ſinner to here god ſay vnto hym, thy ſinnes be forgeuen thee. Howe comfortable a voyce is this voyce to a trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bled conſcience? howe ſure may we be that our ſowles be healed from ſinne, when we ſhall heare this greate phyſytion of our ſowles god almyghty thus to ſpeke vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs? who beinge deſeaſed in his ſowle wyll not make ſpede to heare this voyce? Nay, but ye wyll ſaye, yf we myght heare god ſo ſay,<note place="margin">Iohn. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> it were much more comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then all this is, but who euer harde hym ſo to ſay in the ſacrament? Mary euen thou man that aſkeſte this
<pb facs="tcp:5395:46"/>queſtion, and euery faythfull and true penitente per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For doſt not thou reade in the .xx. Chapiter of ſaint Iohn, that Chryſte ſaythe to his prieſtes, that whoſe ſinnes the prieſte forgeueth, he doth forgyue them, and the ſinnes that be not forgyuen by the prieſtes, are not forgyuen by him. Se nowe I pray you good Chriſten men and women and ye do not here god ſayinge to you that your ſinnes be forgyuen you, when ye heare the prieſt ſay that by the authoritie whiche God hath gyuen vnto hym to abſolute you, he doth abſolute you, ye here that god doth gyue to hym authoritie, and ye heare him ſay that accordynge to the authoritie he doth abſolue or loſe you from your ſinnes. Do not you then here God ſay vnto you by hym, that your ſinnes be forgeuen you? Is not the prieſt Gods meſſenger vnto you: Do ye not reade, or here redde his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion, when ye eyther rede, or here redde this text of Gods worde, whoſe ſinnes ye do forgyue, are forgyuen, and whoſe ſinnes ye do not forgyue, are not forgiuen? Wherin then can you doubt, but that your ſinnes be forgyuen. Verely in nothynge, excepte it be in your ſelues, that is bycauſe you your ſelues be not ſory for them, or wyll not confeſſe them, or do feyne and pretende a penitentneſſe, then in very dede ye may well doubt, yf ye thus do, not for wante that is eyther of Gods parte, or of the prieſtes. For yf there be any doubt at all, it muſt be of your ſelues, whether ye be worthy to receaue the benefite of the ſacrament of pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce or nay, be ye therefore ſure of your ſelues, and then ſhall ye haue no cauſe to doubt, but that ye be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to grace ageyne hearynge hym thus to ſay. Further
<pb facs="tcp:5395:46"/>when ye reade in the olde lawe,<note place="margin">Leui. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> that the people when they had offended in breakynge of Gods ordinaunce, came to the prieſtes and confeſſed theyr faultes uppon the heades of a ſhepe, or ſuch lyke, the which the prieſts dyd offer vp for theyr ſinnes, what other can it ſignifie, but that we ſhulde confeſſe our ſelues to the prieſt, and ley our hand (that is) ſtay our ſelues vpon our lambes heade, that is, the deitie of Chryſt gods lambe, whom vnder the fourmes of breade and wyne, the prieſt doth offer for our ſinnes.<note place="margin">Iohan. <hi>1.</hi> Leuiti <hi>14</hi> Math. <hi>8.</hi> Luke. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> When we rede alſo that the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites were bydden to ſhewe the ſores of theyr bodyes to the prieſt, and that our ſauyour dyd bydde thoſe that he had healed of the leproſy, to go and ſhewe them ſelues to the prieſt, are ye not taught therby that we Chryſten men ſhulde open the ſores of our ſowles to the ſight and knowledge of the prieſt? And the prieſt is apoynted of god to deſerue the ſores of mens fowles, as the prieſtes amongſt the Iewes dyd the ſores of the bodye? Do ye thynke that theſe figures had not the truth ſignified by them?<note place="margin">Math. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> The Pharyſeyes when they came to be baptiſed of ſaynt Iohn, and dyd confeſſe theyr faultes, hauinge no ſuch warrandes by god as our prieſtes haue, wolde not they rather haue come yf they had in mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed therto by promeſſe as we be: be you not worſe (as god forbyd you ſhulde be ſo euyll) then theſe wycked Pharyſes were.<note place="margin">Iaco. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Saynt Iames byddeth that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ulde confeſſe our fautes one to another, the which ſaynt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, muſt be vnderſtande that we ſhulde confeſſe oure leſſe offences to our brethren, and the greater to the prieſte. And ſe I pray you howe conuenient it is thus to do, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:5395:47"/>the prieſt is of greater auctoritie to forgiue ſinnes then other men be. For he is firſt the miniſter of god or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned for that purpoſe, and hath the promeſſe whiche other haue not. Ageyne he is the commen mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates or officer of the Churche, by the vertue whereof, lyke as his prayer is the prayer of the whole Churche, ſo is his abſolution or pardon, the abſolution of the whole Church, wherefore we beinge abſolued by hym, are made to be at peace both with god, and with al good men, ſo that good men wyll remytte offences, when the parties with whom they were offended are confeſſed. If I ſhuld reſyte what the auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers haue taught concerninge oure confeſſion to a prieſte, it wolde be to longe.<note place="margin">Origene homile. <hi>2.</hi> ſuper Leui Auguſtine de viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cione in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmorum Luke. <hi>2.</hi> Capi. <hi>4.</hi> Baſil de regulis. <hi>331.</hi> Chriſoſt de digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Capi. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Origene in his ſeconde homily vpon Leuiticus ſayth, that one of the griefes of penaunce is that wee muſte tell our faute to the prieſte. And it is .xiiii. hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeres ſence he witneſſed this doctrine to be taught in the Church. Alſo ſaint Auguſtine ſayth to them that were ſicke, that in our ſickeneſſe we muſt fende for the prieſt, and declare all our whole mynde and conſciente vnto hym. Baſyll that wrote aboue a leuen hundred yeres ago ſayth, that as we ſhewe the ſores of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes to the ſurgen, ſo muſte we ſhewe our ſinnes to the prieſt. Chryſoſtome in his worke which he wrytethe of the dignitie of prieſthod, ſaythe that the prieſtes of the new teſtament haue authoritie bothe to deſerue, and to heale the leproſy of the mynde where the pry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtes of the olde teſtament,<note place="margin">Ambroſe de peuite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Capi. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> onely deſerued the leproſy of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. For the ſame purpoſe I myght reſyte bothe ſaynte Ierome, ſaynt Ambroſe, and many other that teach it
<pb facs="tcp:5395:47"/>to haue byn obſerued euer ſence the Apoſtles tymes, that Chriſten men and women ſhulde confeſſe them ſelues to a prieſt. Thus you ſeyng the ſcripture ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably to teach it, and that the holy Churche hath ſo longe obſerued, iudge ye nowe whether it be more ſafe for you to folowe the doctryne of theſe holy fathers and gloryous ſayntes, or to be ledde with the vayne flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge lyes, of oure maryed fryers &amp; fleſhly miniſters. Furthermore towchynge the maner of your confeſſion to be made, ye ought fyrſt to conſider, what daunger ye be in through ſynne, ye know that ye haue loſt gods fauoure, ye know that all the creatures of god are than bente ageynſt you, you know that then ye be the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uylles. And ye ſe that ſinfull folke hath come alwayes vnto euyll endes, and howe neare your endes ye be, &amp; what they ſhalbe ye know not. Wherfore ye ſeyng your daunger to be ſo greate. Alas what folly is in you that wyll not haſte and runne vnto confeſſion, yea ye muſt, ye muſt I ſay, be in a maner dryuen thereunto. Chryſt byddeth you awake, &amp; wyl ye lye ſtyl and ſlepe? It were for your ſafety to come euery weeke to confeſſion, and wyll ye thynke much to come once or twyſe in lent? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condely I pray you call to your remembraunce who it is that ye make your confeſſion vnto: It is not in dede to the prieſt, but to God. The prieſt is but his miniſter and deputie, and there appoynted for your cauſes (that is) bycauſe we be ſo dul to conſider the thynges that we ſe not, and oure hartes and myndes are ſo vncerteyne and wauerynge if they be not ſtayed byſome groſſe and ſencible thynge, therefore to do vs the better to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb facs="tcp:5395:48"/>where about we go, and to make vs the better to prepare our ſelues, and the more diſcretely and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſedly to make oure confeſſion, he hathe ordeyned the prieſte viſible to be ſene, and ſenciblely to be harde, but it is he that heareth our confeſſion. And therefore ſayth the prieſt that he doth not abſolue you by any vertue or authoritie that is in hym, though the prieſte be neuer ſo holy a man, but he ſayth that he doth it by the authoritie that is gyuen to hym of god, Wherefore yf ye wyll call vnto your remembrance, howe oft and howe greuouſly ye haue offended and diſpleaſed almighty god our lord and maſter, vnto whome nowe ye come to make your confeſſion. Howe ſhulde it make you to tremble and to quake? If one that had ſo greuouſly offended the king as ye haue offended god, ſhulde be a ſuter to the kinges owne perſon for his pardon, wolde he not tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble trowe ye? And if the kynge wold delyuer his great ſeale vnto the ſcollyan of his kytchen, and commaunde hym to make a pardon for the traytour or offendoure, thynke you that the offendour wolde therefore refuſe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, bycauſe it is delyuered to him by the ſcollyan? No wot ye wel he wolde not. Humble you then your ſelues in lyke maner vnder the almyghty hande of God. And be ye content to receaue your pardon accordynge vnto Gods ordinaunce. Thyrdely I beſeche you to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that Godde vnto whome ye make your confeſſion knoweth all your doynges before that ye ſpeake them, hym ye can not deceaue. And doth not he ſay vnto you in his prophet Eſai.<note place="margin">Eſai. <hi>43.</hi>
               </note> Confeſſe fyrſt thy fautes, that thou mayſt be iuſtified? Se here, he requyreth of you that
<pb facs="tcp:5395:48"/>ye ſhulde confeſſe your fautes. Wherefore deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threne, ſeinge that ye muſte tell to hym your fautes, whom ye can not deceaue, and ſeinge for the confeſſing of them he promyſeth you pardon, be not tryſters, be not deſſemblers in your confeſſion, be not mockers of God, and deſpyſers of his holy ſacramente. Lette not the preſence of the prieſte make you to be aſhamed to ſpeake and confeſſe that, that ye were not aſhamed to do in the ſyght of God. Is it not more ſhame to do euyl the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpeake vppon it? Ought ye not to drede God more then man? If ye be nowe aſhamed to ſay what ye haue done, in the hearynge of a man. Alas lette that ſhame make you afterwardes to remember howe muche more ſhamefull it is to do the ſame openly in the ſyght of god. Learne you that be ſo lothe nowe that a man ſhulde knowe your fautes, ſhe which are not vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to god, what griefe wyll it be to you at the day of dome, when as all your abhominable and ſhamefull wordes and dedes ſhalbe publyſhed abrode to the face of al An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gels, men, and deuyls: ye that be ſo lothe to make one man pryuie to your doynges, howe aſhamed ſhall you be at that day. And verely yf be lothe to tell a ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tale to your ghoſtly father, then do nothinge that is ſhamefull, and ſo ſhall ye want that griefe. If ye caſte ſhame from you for the deuyls pleaſure when he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you to euyl: why ſhulde ye not be content to beare ſhame for gods pleſure when he moueth you to grace? Here is requyred of you but that ye wolde do ſo muche for god in your confeſſion, as ye do for the deuyll in his euyll workes. Wherfore good people, to make an ende,
<pb facs="tcp:5395:49"/>I beſeche you for gods loue to beare in your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce howe honeſte in our behauoure we Chryſten men ought to be: Alſo howe foule and ougly a thynge ſinne is, then by whom, and in what meane ye may be dyght from it, and finally vſe the ſame meane to your conſolation and comfort, and to gods glory, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the father, the ſonne, and the holy ghoſt, be al honour and prayſe nowe and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London in Fleteſtrete at the ſigne of the Faucon ageynſt ſaynt Dunſtones Church by VVyllyam Gryffyth, and are to be ſolde at his ſhop a lyttle aboue the Condyte at the ſigne of the Gryffin.</p>
            <p>Cum priuilegio.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5395:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
